public hearing sycamore ridge we have attorney albert who will conduct the public hearing
for this evening can you hear me in back testing testing okay there you go does this one work okay can i yes okay can you hear me now yeah a little bit okay a little bit too well okay we'll start from the top before the planning commission gets to its traditional uh agenda items we have one special item tonight pursuant to the flexible residential development option contained in the city zoning ordinance the planning commission has jurisdiction over flexible residential development plans which is what has been submitted here and which we are considering tonight the applicant has requested preliminary and final plan approval uh what will happen is here is that this is because this board makes decisions rather than recommendations this particular hearing will be in a more formal way than planning commission meetings are generally run this will be run more like a zoning hearing in which witnesses will be sworn in and we will receive testimony in a more formal fashion than the kind of free discussion that goes on in Planning Commission proceedings we will hear from the applicant first since the applicant has the burden of proof the Commission may certainly ask questions I may have some questions the audience will be given an opportunity to ask questions the city it's my course is always a party to a proceeding in its jurisdiction and I believe the city will have testimony regarding this application and we'll hear from anybody else who wants to be heard I once will say that if you feel that someone else has made your point with the board does not really need to hear it again if your point hasn't been made then we'll be happy to hear it but you know we do want to avoid repetitious testimony if we can okay as you are probably aware we're starting a little bit late because the board conducted an executive session with me that's a prerogative of zoning hearings where the board is allowed to meet with a solicitor privately to get legal advice on how the case will go after the board hears the case this evening the board may very well wish to conduct another executive session in that case the board will adjourn to a private room upstairs where it can consult with me discuss the case among themselves and hopefully after that come to a vote the options are to grant final plan approval to grant preliminary plan approval to agree to continue this case within the time requirements of the municipality's planning code or to deny the plan because it's incomplete if there would be a denial of the plan on the basis that it's incomplete that is not a ruling on the merits of the case it's simply saying that at this time we don't feel uh the formalities of the flexible residential development option ordinance have been met and the applicant will have the right to come back at a later date with a more complete plan if we do take an executive session i'm mindful that there's other business and we'll try to do that as quickly as we can but that may be the case before i begin i would ask lauren finn uh was uh are you aware of whether the agenda was put on the city website and uh was avail posted on the building here at least 24 hours before the hearing it was thank you very much and are copies of the agenda available here for the public yes thank you that's a formality of the sunshine act that we need to comply with okay on that basis then uh unless there's any questions about how we'll proceed i will turn the case over to the applicant and whoever is going to be presenting the case in the applicant please identify yourself to the court reporter and you will be sworn or affirmed and you can proceed burning this song can everybody hear
me okay well good evening planning commissioners and members of the public my name is joe magavero my business partner here is mark peteritis we are longtime residents of lancaster county and together we own mplr holdings over the next 15 minutes we're excited to return to the planning commission to update you on how the plan for sycamore ridge in sunnyside has progressed since we last presented to you our sketch plan and while we still have much to do we are seeking approval of this tentative plan submission so that we can continue it continuing moving it forward in the process for a final plan there's been a lot of buzz around the sunnyside peninsula recently and we think that's really great much of that uh started with the city comprehensive plan rollout and a huge theme as illustrated in green here is the adopted land use map is committing heavy investment in supporting outdoor wreck and revitalization of the conestoga river we're already seeing the exciting beginnings of a nature preserve environmental center and start starting to take shape on the northern portion of the peninsula and on the southern portion in sunnyside hashton yellow here on the screen includes a future land use overlay for a residential eco district and while most people don't even know what an eco district is i think it's accurate to take it's an accurate take on the intent that is to inspire developers like us to think outside the box to ensuring that the residential portion of sunnyside stays special stays unique not just generic housing for the sake of housing so we truly believe in the overall comprehensive plan and the vision of the for the peninsula as it as long as it does not forget the key ingredient which is people the sunnyside really needs a community of people invested homeowners that can sustainably live and thrive on the peninsula after all what what good is a nature preserve or anything really if there's no people there to enjoy it so there's it's no secret the peninsula has accumulated a history of nuisance land uses over the years due to poor planning and you know housing is housing and forests have been replaced with limestone quarry and salvage facility juvenile detention center people live here too but certainly not ideal there's a lot to undo and although the city hasn't adopted any regulation to support a change in zoning from current r3 to ecodistrict achieving success will not will not be about conforming sunny side to typical city ordinances it will be just the opposite requiring both a developer with a unique vision and a planning staff that is willing to boldly guide them beyond conformity so two years ago i tested this theory i had the honor of standing in front of you to earn approval for the first land development project on the sunnyside peninsula in over a century literally 101 years later we built a pair of 800 square foot riverside cottages you can find them at twinsicamore.com they are short-term rentals and our family really enjoys going down and appreciating the neighborhood as well but they were uniquely designed for sunnyside as a nod to the original vision the original vision of the neighborhood when it was first developed in 1912. this land was the plan was unanimously approved and it was even applauded not because it conformed perfectly to city ordinances it didn't it was approved because of the care and thoughtfulness that went into ensuring that they fit we took we fit the our project into the existing fabric of what makes sunnyside magical and for city planners that's the mark of true leadership by supporting this project they weren't sacrificing safety or quality they saw that while sunnyside was a city neighborhood it certainly didn't look anything like the city they rightly saw that is a good thing and ultimately helped us get relief on ordinances that were just not applicable I think it's also important to understand the difference between building codes and standards and ordinances building codes provide engineered direction on how to create roads or structures that don't fail it's what keeps us safe we don't want to mess with these these are these are non-negotiables but ordinances on the other hand are local laws designed to help municipalities create uniformity beyond building code ensuring roads and structures look and feel specific ways that conform to their objectives and goals so thanks to you and the work of the staff our small little project down here came to fruition and end up being a really great success on multiple levels these homes really do fit in we've enjoyed getting to know our neighbors many of them are here tonight sunnysiders are some of the kindest nicest people i have ever met and i'm proud to be a part of this community but it's also been a bit convicting i mean there's a lot to do down here which is why we felt led and qualified to take on this much larger project our vision for sycamore ridge was heavily inspired by mount gretna a thriving woodland retreat at lebanon county a lot of the original 1912 vision for sunnyside and rocky springs feel very similar to what they're what's going on at mount greta and i think it's the closest example we could find at least locally to what an equitable eco district might even look like in sunnyside i mean could you imagine if instead of building juvie center a junkyard in the quarry if somebody decided to build mount gretna and sunnyside all those years ago how different things would be in addition to Mount Gretna Ross Chapin and his book pocket neighborhoods really were a big inspiration for us as well we ended up hiring Ross as a consultant to help us with our site design and pocket neighborhoods just for to explain what that is it's a group of houses clustered around shared open space it's not a one-size-fits-all thing they can vary in shape and size but ultimately they're designed to protect to provide a protected environment for people to live and be outside in nature engage with their neighbors so put those inspirations together and this is what we came up with this is Sycamore Ridge and Sunnyside the vision of Sycamore Ridge is blending Sunnyside's existing woodland community infrastructure with the added charm of a modern-day Mount Gretna and the lifestyle and feel of a pocket neighborhood all right here in city this will be a unique residential nature community that respects the history of the one before it yet boldly leads by example through thoughtful design and sustainable future and similar to our twin sycamore cottages this housing will be smaller and more energy efficient than most new home construction they are simple but elegant homes built with locally struck locally sourced materials making them easy to maintain enjoyable to live in we define this as sustainable market rate housing that's affordable by design they will be available for sale and they will generate over a million dollars per year in combined tax base of the city school district and county it's a big deal and they'll be mixed there'll be a mix of single family detached and semi-detached units that are two and three bedroom layouts with floor plans ranging in between 12 and 1800 square feet two off-street parking spaces will be uh will be there as well with a combination of integrated driveways and garages there will also be main floor living concepts available for 55 plus and multi-gen living these homes will also be heated and cooled with renewable geothermal systems which is just one of the many eco district design components we've integrated within our plan and outlined in our consistency letter we've taken a holistic approach to sustainability and incorporated design elements that address low lower energy improve living systems reduce water reduce waste improves wellness and all contributing to an equitable community here's the site plan we presented to you guys the last time time we were here and just to orient everybody north is to the to the left of the screen so that's where like the environmental center the quarry would be on the right side of the screen is where Duke Street would be so in preparation for a day I went back and watched the sketch plan presentation we had on YouTube and I gotta tell you I I was really excited and encouraged by the energy you guys had in the remarks your recommendations were very good ones and we took them to heart so this is what we've come up with since we've been here last and I know this is very hard to see right here so we we made a little bit more of a presentation version to look at while we talk but by far the number one recommendation we were here last you guys wanted to remove that parking lot from the center of our area and we did it and while we're we weren't able to to remove the entire cart path due to fire safety and ada access to our clubhouse we made it as small as possible it's a 14 foot one-way alley with no purpose other than to enhance community interaction the overall guest parking has also been reduced from the original 30 spaces to now 16 which are all now dispersed throughout the development and not just in one place giving purpose uh also giving purpose as some are even equipped with ev chargers and hookups suitable for food trucks and in service trucks for community events and neighborhood programming as for your feedback around strengthening the infrastructure for community recreation activities our plan now has again clubhouse with a designated ada parking community garden numerous pavilions park benches sitting areas large open spaces for free play a natural amphitheater and one of my favorites a primitive play area similar to what's installed at the new school on columbia avenue i'll touch a little bit more on on this later but the addition of self-storage is also now a component of our community infrastructure um as it's tied specifically to recreation getting people outside and allowing for smaller and therefore more affordable eco-friendly housing and lastly you asked us to consider creative ways of providing more density the short answer is we have and if this is the best we can do first and foremost of the 79 units that are shown here 69 of them are duplexed so they're they're the single-family detached 69 of the yes there's 10 left over the second main obstacle here is that Public Works has only provided us a willingness to serve for sewage capacity for the 79 units here so here is the same plan that you're just looking at just a bit more zoomed out to help you get a little bit bigger picture spatially you can see my big red arrow there that's the South Duke Street bridge and just after that on the left there are four city streets going into Sunnyside remember this is this is not a cornfield in the middle of nowhere this is an existing neighborhood And while there's only 35 or 40 houses back here, currently, it was originally developed and engineered with hundreds of lots. So therefore, access to Sycamore Ridge will simply mirror the same main entry points via South Duke Street. One by way of Davis Street, shown in green. The other, Parkway, to Circle, shown in orange. Which will ultimately, it is and it will continue to be the main connector for Pleasant Street. it's shown in blue there davis would specifically connect travelers to south and the eastmost sides of the development and parkway would connect travelers to the north and westmost sides of the development so if you were to drive into sunnyside on davis using the green line you'd first pass a few residential homes and then right before getting to our new development you'd pass Sunnyside Mennonite Church on your left. Believe it or not, beyond our property and cities, Sunnyside Mennonite Church is actually the next largest landowner on the peninsula. Over the years they have strategically accumulated neighboring lots and even portions of Parkway, as you can see here in the red, in anticipation for possible future expansion opportunities that they might have. Because of this, we took that very seriously. We included them in over six months of our planning and discussions post sketch plan that we met with you numerous entry alternatives were proposed with the church and staff which ultimately resulted in this configuration and as you can see existing public right-of-ways for Davis and Pleasant Street shown in the yellow there have been utilized and reoriented to achieve proper entry to Sycamore Ridge but also their church off of Davis without involving any of their property And this allows us to maintain proper street grades, which was a problem last time we met with you, existing utility connections, but it's great that we also can still have room to install nine new parking spaces for the church. We're committed to being a good neighbor here and are eager to see their mission thrive and grow in the future as well. And while I'm here, this is a good time, I think, to also highlight the transition of public to private streets. it's a little odd I know for that to happen in the city but the green represents existing public streets and there's existing residents here too so in the yellow you can see there there's existing residences that need to maintain public access so that's a lot of the reason we designed the way the streets the way we did in the blue you can see where the streets transition to private and of course that's after after those homes and to be clear the streetscape in Sunnyside currently looks like this so among other things like stormwater volume control and a lot of different the look and feel of these streets the size of these rates privatizing them is very intentional as it provides from an ordinance perspective the opportunity for us to maintain the same woodland alley like look and feel that's already seen throughout the neighborhood all right almost almost done finishing up this little tour we have my little red arrow here that is just about where this rendering is has a perspective so this is the eastmost streetscape through Sycamore Ridge and it's a continuation of the Davis Street so heading north along the wooded ridgeline overlooking the Conestoga River and the first house here on the on the left is actually unit 41 on our site plan it backs up to in is traditionally kind of a pocket neighborhood feel so it has the back opens up to a beautiful open space and has a very a pavilion close by the the first house on the right is number 13 on our site plan and it has an amazing view it's all it's lofted up on on the cliff and uh really dense mature forest overlooking the conestoga river it's absolutely gorgeous people will want to buy one or the other there's a lot of things here but i think what i wanted to showcase here is that while number 13 on the right doesn't necessarily conform to a typical pocket neighborhood concept it's still intimately connected due to our thoughtfully uh done trail system in lieu of just street sidewalks so going back to the site plan you can see my little red Arrow and unit 13 up there I mean look how close it is to everything within less than 40 yards you could walk to the clubhouse and pick up your mail or maybe you're meeting up with a guest if you live in you know unit 13 meet up at a pavilion for dinner and your guests can pull up and charge their cars while while they're having dinner with you maybe residents of number 13 have a garden plot and that's a quick walk as well and instead of only having a small window of time that matches your kids attention span like mine they actually all right you could actually get some quality gardening done because the kids can roam free here and hang out at the park in a very safe environment residents of number 13 might also love mountain biking or the trails in the county park or maybe even the new trails at the Nature Preserve you can see my little red arrow there they simply could walk down to the storage unit grab their bikes and go and as alluded to earlier in addition to the housing component we've also been approved by zoning to install a small amount of self storage and while out of context this might seem a little odd I assure you it's not it's very intentional this is a an older rendering that we have but I think it really does a good job showcasing just how thoughtfully integrated this offering will be for the development both functionally and aesthetically we're excited about this because it not only meets the storage need of our smaller housing stock but it also caters to the many outdoor enthusiasts in the city right now and in the future allowing them to store bikes kayaks canoes all within walking distance of future public river access greenway trails and even the county park nearby you get the picture this is gonna be awesome but as beautiful and all as awe-inspiring as this all is what you see in this rendering here couldn't be farther from conforming to lancaster city ordinance we were very upfront with this the first time we came and stood before you and it's still very much the case today everything from city streets from the street widths the curbs sidewalks and the way our storm waters even manage it's all been customized to blend in the new with the old with as little site disturbance is possible and as you probably saw in our letter this is not something that city staff is used to seeing every day their job is typically to ensure plan submissions conform to ordinances this one literally is designed intentionally not to conform so in the last two minutes of our presentation I wanted to and of course before we open up to questions I wanted ask Douglas Smith for some of you know to offer a few closing comments about the project and its path forward as we enter in the process thank you thank you
Joe good evening Planning Commission members of the public friends colleagues esteemed former mayor's chiefs of staff developers other dignitaries my name is Douglas Smith. I'm a certified urban planner and serving as consultant for the Sycamore Ridge project. Previously I worked for the city of Lancaster for 10 years on a variety of community development and infrastructure projects and most recently held the position as chief planner for the city. I now work for the U.S. Green Building Council as director of location land use where I advise on sustainability policy for a variety of environmental certification products. I'd like to offer some closing thoughts on this project and thank you Joe for and Mark for having me. During my 10 years with the city I helped oversee a historic level of investment during that time nearly every development project required waivers modifications negotiations and novel strategies to get the job done whether it was affordable housing a hospital expansion or a small commercial facility um nearly every one of them received some kind of relief from the planning commission or another board so i just wanted to set that context in terms of what the historic trajectory has been in terms of accomplishing uh projects in the city and i don't think that this project is any different in the way that it it needs some a unique solution although the particular context here might be a little bit different so i'd like to pick up on one of the last things that joe said about how this project doesn't neatly conform to standard ordinances sycamore ridge is pursuing the flexible residential development option and for that reason because of the zoning ordinance section 300-23 is intended among other things to allow innovations and creativity within the tract regarding arrangement of structures dwellings and related infrastructure and sorry i missed the first part there to allow for development on lots with physical constraints such as steep slopes this project undoubtedly meets this the intent of this section of the ordinance so the special filing was designated for these kinds of unique projects and it gives the Planning Commission special powers to help provide relief so we're inviting you all the Planning Commission to think outside the box with us and consider what might need to be done differently on this project flexible residential development typically accomplished as a tentative plan followed by a final plan with one caveat the small text there and i'll just paraphrase for you the planning commission holds the power to approve a tentative plan as a final plan if it meets all the requirements of a final application i want to make clear to the commission this evening that we're we'd like to take a different tact on this we've revised we'd like to revise our request and ask you to consider a tentative plan approval instead this will help us have your reassurance or your your buy-in from Planning Commission so that we can proceed with addressing the more technical comments with the city with with more confidence can you repeat the
revision of your request I'm not sure I followed it sure so the agenda
advertised that the developer was seeking to forego a tentative plan and seek a final plan approval so in lieu of that the revised request is that the Planning Commission consider a tentative plan approval okay rather than going straight to final now it was it was listed under modifications that I don't think that's technically a modification but just wanted to make clear that we're changing our request now I want to touch on the planning process just for a moment. I've grouped these decision by decision making body not as a timeline but I want to let you know that this project has been before the zoning hearing board and it's achieved a special exception for self storage. The county planning commission is scheduled to review this project on October 14th for consistency with its land use plan at the county level. City Planning Commission you all have been involved in the sketch plan. We appreciate all your comments there. You heard from Joe on that tonight is satisfying the tentative plan public hearing which is required. And then the last one on that list would be seeking tentative conditional plan approval by November 16th which is 60 days after the public hearing ends if it ends tonight. And then that would that actually the meeting that would have to be heard that would be November 5th. So that's the next planning commission meeting before this date passes. and I'm sorry I have the date wrong on it says 9-17 but oh yeah it is yeah sorry that's correct um okay so moving on to just a couple of final things I wanted to give you a peek at what's coming next if this plan were to proceed so this is these are some of the approvals that are needed for the final plan process there are a couple of state approvals needed for sewage and for storm water both the shade tree commission and traffic commission would be required to review this plan and take action on it as well that typically comes towards the end of the final plan process so that we have all of our details you know straight and the city has reviewed things we have other approvals from PPL electric to City Council also needs to act on portions of this plan they would be approving the planning module for sewage any street dedication or vacation and potentially other agreements if that if those are required and then finally the Planning here would be reviewing the plan as well probably once at least once or maybe two times followed by an action on it so that's the trajectory that we're looking at here and I would encourage you to learn more about the project scan the QR code go to the website sign up for updates a couple of final closing thoughts before we open up to questions and I'm sorry I've exceeded my two minutes that I was allotted when I started working in the city I reviewed the last sunny side plan that some of you may remember that project although I had different kinds of benefits than this one it did propose clear-cutting most of the forests on the peninsula installing 350 units on the peninsula building to the edges of the floodplain hardly providing any recreational area for residents and in my opinion not much of a forward-thinking environmental vision. I held these lessons in mind while I served as one of the primary authors for the city planning commission's adoption of the comprehensive plan and I helped brainstorm with residents staff and this commission about the future of Sunnyside and that vision that we all came to collectively included an environmentally friendly development like Sycamore Ridge and an environmental center. And that vision has captured the imagination of the community and attracted potentially millions of dollars the high foundation and others and i really see sycamore ridge as trying to achieve that vision and does require doing things a bit differently and i'm encouraged by that so i'm glad to be here tonight and see you all and i look forward to listening carefully to all your comments thank you
does the applicant have any other witnesses normally this would be the time where the commission would throw this open for questions it has been my experience in 50 years of doing this that people who attend these hearings seldom ask just questions they ask the question and then they go right into making their statement for or against so to avoid that kind of chaos what we're going to do is hear from the city of lancaster next who is a party and has a position statement and then we will throw it open for questions comments anything you want to do so if you'll be bear with us for just a moment folks you you will have you will have a chance to be heard this is a public hearing everyone will get their say okay at this point i would ask the city of
lancaster has any representative present yes this is betsy logan i'm the planning bureau chief for
the city okay would the court reporter please swear her in thank you okay um you have the floor
um thank you yes so the city um staff has reviewed the submittal for the tentative review of sycamore ridge and while the administrative administration has been working with the applicants on sycamore ridge at sunnyside at this point there are some elements that are lacking in the submission that need to be addressed prior to final plan approval because it is a specific flexible residential development there are numerous requirements that still need to be met even though it is to provide flexibility on development we have provided the applicant with our staff report outlining numerous issues that we are not able to provide feedback like more detailed feedback on because we're still unclear as to what like the solution would be or how they're proposing to do certain things in what respects is the application incomplete so while they submitted all the specific criteria that's required there's not enough detail on stormwater sewer water lines there's some more information that's needed for zoning and it's kind of hard to provide a full
length of all the well uh if if the if this board has to make if this board is to take action uh the board either well preliminary plan approval because final plan approval is off the table for the night the board first of all has to satisfy itself whether or not the application is complete and ready for consideration and if the city has a view that it's not the specific reasons would need to be placed on the record so the board can make an informed
decision sure so um some of the zoning issues that are outlined in the letter are related to
the calculation for density excuse me by the letter are you referring to a letter of september
8th 2025 to you yes it was prepared by c.s davidson as well as our general group of people who do plan review which includes public works right away environmental concerns storm water sewer water zoning general subdivision and land development um so all of those people
have reviewed okay and based on that letter what are the city's specific concerns about
the incompleteness of this application so zoning wise there are some questions on parking calculations and how they were determined as well as building density calculations in addition as part of a flexible residential design architectural renderings are required and
we did not receive slow down the court reporter people can read a lot faster than the court
reporter can take it down okay and architectural rendings are required for the self-storage buildings um there are some concerns regarding well i guess the biggest concern that we have is as submitted the application included three properties that currently the city of lancaster owns back in january of this year we had conversations with the applicant regarding the potential to swap properties in february the applicant's attorney received information from our solicitor that at this time the city was not interested in doing that but those properties were still included in this application okay for planning comments the developer needed to submit the written response to all the sketch plan comments that wasn't received with the application and they need to address the changes as joe outlined in his presentation like that would need to be addressed in writing as a sketch plan review um common letter okay that that was uh that was in 2024 yes it was dated september 16 2024. okay anything else um as far as what's missing from being able to make a decision on it we the sewage planning module has not been submitted yet we would need hoa documents to review and including documents that outline how the commercial self-storage is going to be working we don't have sewer and water will serve letters they were not provided with the application um profiles on roads water storm sewer and sewer were not provided um which would be needed in order and additionally cross road cross sections were not included to ensure compliance with the subdivision and land development there was a request for a waiver to reduce the length of how frequently the profiles need to be provided that is included in this application i have to say you've always dropped off i'm sorry sorry there's a request for a waiver related to how many profiles they need to provide um that was included in their application okay was that waiver acted upon or was that for for the commission that's for the planning commission okay what's the city's position on whether that waiver should be granted um in our discussion regarding it we don't feel that it should be granted because of the steepness of the property we would like to see more consistent profiles which would be standard in any application uh you'll have to i'm not an engineer
you'll have to explain to me why the steepness of the property relates to the number of cross
sections you want to see i'm also not an engineer so i don't know that i can provide feedback on
that as far as being incomplete there are concerns with over the past year as
we've worked with the applicant they had gone away from the Davis Street entrance so we've had numerous conversations related to expanding the Parkway entrance and as access when they did come to submit the plan that went back to Davis street so those conversations that were had that kind of had a process outlined and what needed to be provided changed and so there's not enough detail on what they're proposing for the Davis entrance water and sewer comments would include there's a water line that would need to be provided to address proper fire flow pressure we've been working with the applicant on where that should be located coming from the partners for environmental stewardship in the city property that was not provided on the plan survey of the city's existing sanitary sewer facilities around the project area is also needed to be provided there are concerns too regarding the downstream capacity of the city's sanitary sewer another concern that we have is that a phase one or phase two environmental study were not provided as part of the submission they did reference it in some other documentation however we have not seen any of that and the remediation for that needs to
be more detailed is a phase two environmental study required by the application I could not
answer that question specifically um generally we tend to require it if there if we know that there's environmental concerns with digging and it used to be a scrap yard for automobiles
okay has one been requested of the applicant it was included in the letter okay thank you
anything further um there's several stormwater concerns um the biggest one being that the modeling um didn't look at the correct storm flow events and the correct um runoff i think they need to do 1.25 and that wasn't what was provided and so that's generally what we feel is what's missing
from the application anything else um not at this time um the letter of september 8th um okay of 2025 that letter was that letter shared with the applicant yes it was provided to the applicant on september 8th okay did you receive any formal response any response to that we had a follow-up
meeting regarding the letter um monday of this week the 15th and then another follow-up meeting
yesterday with the applicant what is the city's position regarding this application at this time
the city does not believe that it's ready for tentative land development approval there's some large questions that need to be considered especially considering it's a planned residential development process and has very specific requirements that need to be met before the city could take action on approving anything before we open up to the audience i'm
certainly going to give the applicant a chance to respond to the statements made whoever wants
to speak uh let's let's hear from them so we um we very much understand that there's a lot of work to be done i think part of these larger projects douglas mentioned a lot of items like shade tree commission hoas there's a lot of things that traditionally are left to final plan submission there there's a lot of detail going on in this project and any project that's a size and so some of the we got this September 8th and again we did not get a whole lot of time to review or get back and forth we're talking about two days ago so yes there are things that you know everybody has this information there are there are items that we need to discuss and figure out our engineers have been looking at it um talking to their engineers i'm a glass half full guy i don't think any of these issues are issues that are going to stop the project where there's a will there's a way and there seems to be a way it's just going to take time and so i think with the the concept of the flexible land development plan we chose this route because it all it seemed like the only route that made sense to do something so out of the ordinary the comprehensive plan calls for it to be out of the ordinary and so we showed up today with a formal preliminary plan and we were asking you to vote on it there's no way that you should say yay it's not complete as a preliminary plan in a formal sense but as a tentative plan absolutely I think it's far enough along the stormwater for instance we far exceed certain ideas I'm not an engineer so I'm not gonna go into detail either Betsy and I are not engineers but what we do know is that our engineers have looked at it they have been talking to each other and there is a path and yeah so anyway I don't want to take too much time on this we can dive into specific items if we need to but all of these items are very very achievable there's no way we'd be able to walk through each of these holding holding the the timeline legal timeline that the tentative plan has and so I think the flexibility of this route allows for us to get tentative approval and allows us to keep moving keep getting things done and just checking systematically checking things off the list this is not an approval of a final plan in any way shape or form and is not prepared as a final plan in any shape or form yeah I
just i guess one of the questions i mean over here that's no problem um so you know for the example of the city-owned properties that you include in your plan i mean that seems like a pretty big deal if you can't get those properties so i'm just like there i totally understand you know that you're requesting some flexibility and i think you know as a planning commission we're we're definitely uh interested in that conversation but for like those are that's a a pretty big issue so for the bigger issues could you give us some context
yeah specifically for the the land swap that was honestly a mistake on our part we we don't have a full-time attorney dedicated to this project there's no attorney at representing us today and we're doing that very intentionally this is it's a very unique project so we wanted to be delicate and personal with this our attorney apparently received this notification in February and we never got word of that it sounds like a simple mistake at the same time I have not had access to the solicitor I've not had access to the mayor I don't know how much conversation there has been at all about these properties but it we can we can bring them up but they're they're three very I don't want to say worthless because it valuable to somebody but they're they're they're wooded cliffside that it's unusable for any kind of any kind of development and it is weirdly toothed into our frontage so it's certainly worth with a phone call we just haven't had that phone call and we we specifically have three lots that are very close to what seems to be where like a public access to the future public access to the river and quarry would be that directly abuts the city some city land as well and we figured like we have no purpose for these I think in the grander good of you know the comprehensive plan I think they'd be really interested in those so I don't know if we're buying or trading but I I think it's just a matter of a conversation I don't see why this city solicitor would want not do something like that so I guess just one follow-up
is is your how dependent is your plan on those properties like is there it's not
it's annoying again it's a mistake I'll be frank it was a mistake but it's annoying yeah so if we can't get that done we have to redraw and massage around the layout okay so again like if I had access to the mayor to ask hey would you would you think this is a great idea like I don't know what you're doing with this but it's just sitting here we can make some good use of it and we have those over here that i think you could make really good use of i think that's really all it takes if we get a no whatever we'll just massage the layout um so i'm a little concerned
with the lack of the presentations of the city of the environmental review i personally feel that article 1 section 27 of the constitution of pennsylvania which makes the commonwealth a trustee of the public natural resources also requires the city and it's purview to be a trustee as well so why have you not yet disclosed that to the city i
don't know what that means you're talking about the environmental uh testing and a review or any
of those items you want to talk about okay good evening mr dastra yeah you're talking about the uh i think the phase one phase two environmental review um so there's some contamination on site from the junkyard um and i'll let you me or mark give you the updates on where exactly that stands but there's planned or has been excavation there and so the phase one is the assessment of what contamination is there the phase two is the actual remediation of that area all of that the phase one is done the phase two will be underway and that soil will be removed from the site which is of great benefit to the community. It's beyond the stormwater infiltration requirements that the city may ask us to prove does not interfere with contaminants on site. There's there's nothing in the SALDO that I'm aware of that would require us to provide the phase one and phase two but that was not intentionally withheld for any particular reason at all. And I think we'd be happy to provide that all of that documentation to the city. And you know I think this project is very proud to be removing that contamination that has been sitting in the community for decades.
So applicants willing to give the city those documents.
Yes yeah we can provide those. And just to give a quick summary we were actually really pleasantly surprised during our due diligence period of what the testing showed. It's very very minor very small area and it's very minor. So yeah the contamination that we need to be removed is not something that we were concerned with.
okay that's good um talking about the buildings themselves and i don't know if you have anything to say to this mr smith because this would now be your kind of area um what is the anticipated lead certification level for these buildings uh none and i know you don't want to hear that i really
do know that you don't want to hear that but um and douglas doesn't either it is expensive to do that and we're trying so desperately hard to provide affordable housing without subsidies without so yes we could it would just make the price of these houses go up even higher and it just does not seem like a good idea we already have such a huge issue with affordability and we're again the size the simplicity the design all around is intended to bring the cost of new homes
drastically down that's the that's the real crux of why I mean respectfully in terms of cost I've heard it reported that you're anticipating a three hundred thousand three hundred fifty thousand cost per unit that's already very expensive for members of this community exactly that's concern still I don't think that quite adds up for me um other so you had mentioned earlier that local sourcing will make uh these units easier to maintain and you know you're talking about cost um how this might sound like a big question but like how does that logic hold like what is the guarantee that locally sourcing the materials also makes these easier to maintain um i'm not sure we want to pull pictures
or not but the the the material that where I used on the the cottages is what what we use on pole barns like every day it's like the not-so-fancy standing seam metal and so it's very economical there's lots of options for that and it's practically maintenance free the last 50 plus years we're using a lot of of that in a lot of creative ways and the other items are you know just kind of general wood siding that is you know has long duration guarantees but again you know what sitting on shelves very locally sourced we have lots of Lancaster's awesome it's a melting pot so we have we have an unfair advantage I would say accessing trusses and building materials and so our houses are literally designed with uh with the help of our contractors like what can you get what can you get how can we use this product that you have access to that's how we built the last ones that's how
we're going to build the new ones okay um so it sounds more like it's easy to maintain through simplicity of design rather than a sourcing yeah and the materials themselves i mean this you know
we don't need to paint things you don't need to uh a lot of these materials don't require a lot of maintenance and i think that's that's helpful for lots of generations of people but yeah
you had also said that you tested this theory and it so it works um as i understand it your existing units are short-term rentals so how does those two short-term rentals translate to the success of a i'm counting 79 housing for sale development complex it's completely different market how does that translate to proving that this is good yeah i think uh i think it's one of
those nuanced uh you can't quite put your finger on it but i think it's a um it was a vision and an idea that we had hey can we make this work and can we embed something brand new into a community and it not be overwhelming an alternative would be like we could just go build like a 6,000 square foot wild crazy thing on on the cliff and I don't know if that would jive right that would not fit in at all so I think to that respect that's how we kind of are kind of deriving success the other thing is too like tangible just can we do this we again designed thought through the building process but the construction of those homes was very efficient which again has a direct correlation to cost and so we're we're taking those you know learned processes and applying them again too
you had said that the wooded cliffside is unusable i disagree with that personally in fact i think that using cliff sides can become a remarkably great use for ecological design the insulation the ground provides to the structures you're building within um so i i don't really have a question there i just want to state that for the record that i i think that that doesn't hold water uh the cliff sides are usable it's just you've made a choice to focus on a different type of of design um i'll stop for a second if anybody else has questions a number of questions regarding
the affordability of this project you have called this project an affordable project a number of times um 350 000 starter home is not an affordable starter home we need to lessen the cost of housing within this community the average ami of our lancaster city is sixty three thousand dollars a 60 a person making 63 000 cannot afford to live in that housing development on top of that i'm just curious to know self-storage and some of the amenities on the site i heard the word hoa curious to know what that would add to the cost of the housing particularly itself and then i would just recommend that you remove the word affordable from this market rate would be more appropriate although if you can get the prices down i don't think that would happen because of the capacity of the density um that's part of that's part of my spiel the other part is the fire and safety perspective of this if i recall the last time you gentlemen um stood in front of us there were some serious concerns regarding fire safety and access to the water the pressure specifically if there were two fires on either side of that community which we hope would never happen currently it's my understanding that there is not a way to have capacity to serve both of those homes depending on where they're located one of those hydrants could only be running per at a time so I'm curious to know a little bit more about that and I'll pause for a
second yeah let's talk about sure let's jump in on the fire safety issue first because that's really important so we we were flagged by the fire chief that was an issue that there's in you know insufficient supply as you noted and the solution for that is to bring further supply from the north end of the peninsula near the juvie center where there is an 8-inch main currently today So we've been talking with the city team and with the high foundation associated with the environmental center planning and everything else to find a suitable route to bring that down to solve that issue. So it would need to be a condition for this project to move forward.
Great. How about the – let's back up one second because I kind of tossed two things at you at one time. And I'm really curious to go back to the affordability aspect of this project, not so much just as to throw my thoughts out there, but to get some thoughts back from you gentlemen as well um you know i do have concerns um like i said regarding your use of the word affordable um i don't think that this is an affordable first time housing project i um but i'm curious to know in addition to the mortgage that somebody would be paying what additional costs would they have so if i am a prospective resident of your new community and i want to rent one of your storage lockers what will that cost me approximately and i'm also interested to know what my hoa fees would potentially be and what would be included
within that program sure so for hoa we're very early in that but we've estimated it to be somewhere in the like 80 range per month we're trying to keep that very low we don't have a pool and tennis courts and that kind of thing instead we have outdoor recreation as the main attraction and amenity so the goal is to keep it under $100 right now we're landing right around 80 85 dollars a month as far as storage we haven't set pricing or anything for that yet but it would be you know market rate or below market rate we'd have a variety of sizes it wouldn't be primarily associated with cars it would be associated with small storage for bikes kayaks you know things that nature and um did you want do you want me to talk a little bit about the affordability part
because i do think well i i think if your minimum cost is three hundred thousand dollars you just personally i take offense to you using three hundred thousand dollar homes and the word affordability in the same sentence that is not fair not a thing so it's all relative
i appreciate that i appreciate that the the word affordable is directly associated to subsidized i appreciate that being um the issue um affordable is also relative the the average regular home in lancaster city or i think was 386 the last time i saw in lmp and the average new home is 488 so that's lancaster county right now so affordable based on those terms is absolutely affordable but we will try to slow that down or use another word i just think it's really important that we
buy that we are manufacturing realistic housing for the population that we're actually serving i can appreciate that yes the other question i have is in regards to a traffic study and your entrance and exits to and from the development duke street i go down there all the time i essentially could live in county park i run those trails like hundreds of times a week and there has been multiple occasions where i have either almost been hit by a car i can't get out of where i'm coming from so i am not particularly pulling in and out of sunnyside but i'm very familiar with the you know safety of that street and particularly at certain times of day the traffic is a lot is a lot busier now you're going to add let's say 80 homes to round it up with two cars each that's 160 cars going in and out of this site potentially with the current traffic conditions that were already posed on duke street so i'd just like to know a little bit more about what you're doing as far as safety measures to ensure that traffic is entering and exiting that particular property safely and any thoughts on like maybe innovative would you do one way in
one way out like how would you we so we had a we had an engineer a traffic engineer look at the project and determined that the project is exempt from needing to have a traffic study done based on the ordinance there's that we do not we do not know to date if we need to I think we were going to have to go to the traffic commission um as part of this process so that is you know to be determined how that will go but we absolutely will be in front of them as it pertains to the real nuts and bolts of it um again based on where things are at we don't have direct connection to duke street it is not a city street it's a pen dot road um we we absolutely agree with you it is a global issue not a you know sunnyside or sycamore ridge issue and we will absolutely do anything in our power to work towards making that better but i want to be very clear that like we don't really see having a much direct correlation with our plan we have not we have at least not been made aware of those
so just my friends on the city themselves from the traffic study perspective because their engineer suggested that it wouldn't be necessary i find that a little bit hard to believe based off of other plans that we have discussed in previous meetings um so is that a factual thing or will
they actually need a traffic study what they did was they conducted a trip generation and the trick the trip generation then triggers whether or not there is a study needed and so according to their trip generation a study is not needed so according to how they they conducted their trip generation um and then can you go into a
little bit more about the challenges um that the i just want to understand um if i recall the words correctly it was said that the public's works capacity for that development only was would only allow for 79 homes and you have a maximum of 79 homes on that site correct
or you have you have your 79 homes um why so that's important because there's a maximum and so what that means is there can be no future development on sunnyside so if another residence wanted to do an addition at any type of capacity they would not be able to because they would have maxed out the amount of the of the usage is that they would have hit capacity specific to
the sycamore ridge land it wouldn't would that affect it's because of their it's because of
their density it's because of it being 79 houses now we have spoken with the applicant about that who has talked about offering residences this is all based on number of bedrooms and so what the applicant has proposed is offering more residences that have less bedrooms because that will make them it will make the number less and so as you do the as you do the calculation the more bedrooms you have the more sewer capacity you need and so you can you can play with it by having less bedrooms but the point remains that they would they would ultimately max out the sewer usage so there would be like zero room for development on the whole
peninsula I'm sorry on the on the southern are you are you sure about that because that's not the way we interpreted in fact during our due diligence period we were we got a letter saying that there was a hundred and 16 units available and we received our willingness to serve it literally is what it sounds like it's the willingness to serve letter so we have permission to use 27,500 gallons per day of sewer capacity I don't I what I don't don't understand or I don't know is this is new information to me that we're taking up all of that second reason why it's a little bit confusing and unnerving is that by by design and by right every lot is taken in consideration with sewer capacity so when we go in for a development it's an addition to every lot whether it's hooked up or not so I do not agree with the ruling that there no more sewer capacity if there is a lot in length in Sunnyside you should be able to build on that lot by right and hook up to public water and public sewer
right but you might have to you might have to you might have to tap in you
absolutely will have to tap in but that is it is already calculated what they're allowing for is in addition to what's already on the peninsula not saying that
this is the peninsula's capacity that was my understanding I have one final question I'll pose
in the world that I live in things are scheduled by percentage of completion it's been said that the city has shared some concerns regarding the lack of certain details that are missing from this plan so I would like just curious to know what do you think the percentage of completion is from your tentative plan and what do you think the realistic milestones are from the city to get that to a state that the city would feel more comfortable considering to move this project forward and then in regards to that with the follow-up meetings that were had after the letter was received regarding some of those details that need to be addressed how was those communications how was that was you know are you an agreement with the things that are in that letter are you disagreeing with the things that are in that letter and then I'll take a pause there thank you Commissioner
Seifert so I think it's it's a let me start by saying the preliminary plan final plan process that is set up in the SALDO and I would even say maybe even in the state code does not provide for a lot of difference between these two in other words preliminary plans are often expected to have a similar level of engineering unless the municipality allows otherwise as the final plan and that is part of what I think we're up against and having a tentative plan before you where we're trying to get buy-in on I think a good concept and trying to be very you know honest about what we're trying to do and also acknowledge that there's additional engineering that has to be done so I think that that is one of the important issues to note here so as to the percentage complete from you know to the point where we would be constructing you know I of course I did this kind of work for a long time and I'd say you know we're probably somewhere hovering around the 60% mark and that's because there's lot that is often not even always in the public eye or even in the Commission's purview as to what happens even after the plan is conditionally approved here there's often a very long list of agreements that lawyers start to work on and there's a lot of technical comments that have to be done we would have to write the HOA for the Planning Commission the ordinance allows us to actually do that after approval but before recordation all the signatures have to be gathered and the bond needs to be posted and I could go on and on and so all of that does take a significant amount of time to accomplish so I don't want to shortchange all of the work that even has to happen after a conditional approval is given by the commission
you had a second part to your question curious to know if you are in agreement with providing the necessary details that the city is requesting for the letter that was dated on September 8 2025.
I'll let the owners speak to that more directly but I'll just say that I you know I reviewed the letter myself and I think as Joe said these are all issues that can be addressed and where there's a will there's a way and I wasn't personally you know very surprised by any of the comments and I think that we were expecting a lot of them and we know that there is more work to be done. So yeah Joe and Mark do either of you want to elaborate on that.
quick comment um gentlemen right here right here um no you're good um i would just i just have an encouragement uh just kind of going back to what commissioner nicole said about the affordability of your housing um by all means if you have a target resident that you're looking to be in these residents i would encourage you to to mention that because if you take the word affordable and you place it beside hoa hoa all but disqualifies affordable so i would just encourage you moving forward if you are saying that or if you're desiring to have a target resident to say that because it's like a shake in my head moment when i hear you say it's affordable but on one of your slides it says $386,000 starting point so I don't know what world you live in but $386,000 starting to move into a home it's not affordable for a whole bunch of people you guys are really smart men otherwise you want to came up with this plan so
just think about that chew that up a little bit and think on that that's all mr. weeks if I may
just provide one quick follow-up and this is actually for the broader Commission and the room as well but I just wanted to make note of the HOA issue because I know that that word has some connotation to it about what that what comes along with that and the the HOAs have become increasingly common and to be frank part of that is is also driven by our stormwater ordinance what often happens is there's one facility to serve multiple properties or multiple houses and out of affordability for the development there's usually a central facility that then all of these individual houses become responsible for and there has to be some entity that governs that if these are for sale homes and a perfect example of this is actually the affordable homes that are on Chesapeake Street that Saka built that whole neighborhood there is a part of an HOA and there's a stormwater facility at the bottom of it that all of them have to maintain including the parking lot and the more infrastructure that comes along in these projects more expensive those hoa fees become and i think one of the commendable things about this project is uh mark and joe and the designers involved are trying to take a hard look at the amount of infrastructure that they're providing in this project and that is the only reason mark is able to quote a number as low as he just did because i've never even heard of an hov quite that low before so i think that this team is truly working to try to make this a project where there's low maintenance and that requires the repairing buffers to serve as a storm water and that requires it or us to think creatively about how the roads are and curbs and
sidewalks and all the rest by no means am i trying to imply anything these gentlemen have been super transparent with everything you said to this point i appreciate that however i will say i said what i
said totally no thank you mr weeks one last question uh we'll be brief so that the way we
can hear from the public um there's water all around this plane and i know you have a flood plate in that goes within the floodplain limits but I'm thinking climate change that water is rising seven years ago we had Matthew and that kind of Stoker River was just over flooding its banks can these structures can they sustain sustain some of this damage even minimal flooding and will these if I have a mortgage on this on some of these problems will I have to buy I'm sure going to buy flood insurance which will add to that yeah that's a great question um in sycamore
ridge we are uh i think that's probably the one of the one of the nicer things about the site it is very high in elevation compared to the floodplain um so you know we're taking our lickings on steep slopes and complexity in the site but that is certainly one thing that we don't have to deal with we're nowhere near the floodplain the we are utilizing property that we own in a floodplain or around a floodplain specifically for riparian buffer installation and part of our stormwater but no housing will be
anywhere near it may I ask a question one of the things I was looking at in the audience of course we have many members of the audience who were here back in 2014 when the Planning Commission approved essentially a nine page document of modifications that needed to be done for the tentative plan to go through and that was for 300 units I'm just wondering with considering the history of that what will make this different are we looking at nine ten 12 pages obviously a lot has happened in 11 years yeah that is the crux of the
issue I mean I spoke I spoke to this this is a really high-level thing but we really we really would love staff to consider looking at this differently the comprehensive plan while it's not the eco district concept is not embedded in our ordinance we are having to kind of create the airplane while we're flying okay it is not there are no ordinances for what we are doing there's engineering again there's engineering standards and there's engineering best practices and building codes and the alike and there's a lot of ordinances that are in the city that are close but that is our question like do we really need to have nine pages of waivers that you that you y'all need to call through or or can we have our engineer talk to your engineer and and see that it is satisfactory from a again from an engineering standpoint meets those types of things and with an understanding like yeah joe this is actually not meeting ordinance but we support and we verify that this road's good we support and verify that this storm water plan is good we verify and support that your design for layout is good that is what we would really
really appreciate from the planning staff can you help me understand why we should allow you to negotiate through certain processes and procedures when we do not let anybody else do that i don't necessarily
think so i think it's more of a i think it's more of an understanding of intent i'm not asking an engineer to give way or undermine a design i am asking for intent to be appreciated like it like again like the last project was the last project was in the same place i just so happened again because of foresight and thoughtfulness i did not have to put in curbs like that technically was a waiver probably i did not have to install sidewalks that was probably a waiver i did not have to do a lot of things over there because it doesn't make any sense to do that there's not a single sidewalk or curb in sunny side right now and so we're trying again to do this thing and i and i get it um you want the city ordinance is designed to produce streets that look like king street that look like chestnut street not sunny side not davis with all due respect sir i think you're running two issues
together here there's a lot of flexibility in the flexible residential development options that's why it's called that you're allowed to do many things that are otherwise required in the city but the the threshold issue that miss logan has here is whether you have made a complete submission that's meaningful enough so that the city staff can meaningfully review this and that this commission can meaningfully uh act on it and i i see with all due respect i think
they're separate things sir yeah i i understand i i did not i did not absorb the question properly so in that regard i would just refer back to what douglas said i think we're at 60 and i think that's it all all inclusive of every easement and legal document that we have to sign
and and what I'm saying is the 60% I think it's I don't necessarily have a question but it's more of a statement you know this Sunnyside area has a long history of being short-sighted with projects for decades going back decades similar to the community that I came out of we've been short-sighted on many projects and short chains so we and with the things that need to be completed it appears as though the community just deserves more of these things that you to complete because that's what they deserve i believe that you know it's a community that has integrity and wants to develop and and needs to have their best interests in mind and what shows that is more completion and further progress and not you know trying to complete repair the plane as you're flying that's i think that's what you said is that what you said yeah it was a nice metaphor at the time yeah so while you're flying yeah so um that's a statement
and for the record yes yeah i i definitely might have more questions after the public speaks um but before we move forward i just want to say like you know we're talking about about creativity here and I don't think this plan is very creative I think that this is a size-down version of a suburban development that we might see outside of the city where you have larger Lots these might not be McMahon's McMansions but I know a chicken nugget when I see it you're talking about equitable development and you're providing units that are all seemingly roughly the same size so that means that the people who are consuming that only have one option in that neighborhood and to your point about people and nature preserves no people if you don't have people to enjoy it it's not a preserve I don't necessarily agree with that because it's a preserve however to your point about people you're only offering this opportunity to enjoy the environmental things you may hope to provide to a certain type of customer so the lack of diversity of housing types in this development is greatly concerning and I know I brought that up last time I do not see great changes between your original proposed plan and this proposed plan and i think that you could be using the diversity of housing units to not only provide different opportunities for people to live here whether it's affordable or not just different types of family structures you did mention multi generally generational housing i have great concerns that this type of housing cannot provide that as someone who has lived in multi-generational housing not sure because they are rather small it seems from the plan i don't have an exact number on square footage but i do not find this current presentation equitable i do not find it creative and i'm
very upset between this presentation and the one originally proposed okay um i have a question for
you gentlemen um i think we've had a very you know a lengthy but very productive discussion i think we've had you've heard the views of a number of the people here on the commission as well as the views of the city and the the next step is if the hearing continues i will open this up for public comment there are people here uh my question for you and if you wish to consult privately about this is that do you wish to withdraw your application or would you like to hear public comment that's that's that's your call folks it's your application we would like to hear the public comments okay very well uh this is now the time for public comment the applicant has made their statement the city has made its statement count commission has asked its questions whoever would like to be heard for public comment please raise your hand and what i'll ask you to do is uh yes and please uh you like us up in the microphone yes we'll ask whoever wants to comment to come up to the microphone and we'll have you sworn in by the court reporter and then you may make your statement on the record and i've been i've seen you raise your hand right there i'll give
give you the first privilege we are not a 350,000 community we are far from that apparently you want to take them home to Mount Gretna dude you're all base your office mount gretna is an art community they do art shows up there every year people go to the jigger shop they have the theater we don't have that your two houses that you built down back of us was in a floodplain to this day no one knows how you got the okay to build any floodplain because the house that the second one to the left there was a little lean-to built there and the city raised hell about that so how you got to building the floodplain you saw to somebody's pocket and that's all this is about you making billions while we live there we like our little community we don't want to be part of the city where you have all the rich people doing what they're doing because that's not what we're about and you said about our environmental building we got one right across the road in the county park and it has a library why do we need that we don't we want to go to the park we go across the street we don't need it and it's not welcome and I think a lot of them I know we all live among each other but we don't want it the ground that you're trying to build on was a junkyard transmission oil diesel gasoline power steering fluid all went into that ground and you say there's only a some there's decades decades you've been there i've been there yeah i know that decades and it's leaked down into the ground and you can't convince me that there's only it's ridiculous we're not a 350 80 000 community and you want to bring that ain't gonna go we're not coming up there to rent storage so i like i like your one comment that you made affordable people can't afford to live in lancaster cities that's why our homeless rate has going skyrocketed our seniors have to choose between paying their bills or taking their medication not going to a doctor's appointment 350 000 and affordable 100 000 isn't affordable 65 85. bring your prices down there build build buildings like they did on south duke street concrete building not some luxurious building build buildings like that that's affordable like i said that's not even close to mount grunt now that's the top of the hall that you want to
build okay thank you for your comments and uh in light of the large number of people here uh if you can make it keep your comments uh brief that would be appreciated sir yes right right
there you're next good evening um i do dwayne breneman b-r-e-n-e-m-a-n good evening i'm a longtime member of sunnyside mennonite church and i currently serve as our church board chair so my comments tonight are on behalf of the church so while there's there's certainly some excitement for us as a church thinking about having new neighbors we also have some significant concerns with this plan and there's one in particular that i want to draw your attention to this evening as presented the plan would have a significant negative impact on sunnyside mennonite church specifically this plan would reduce substantially our occupancy because it would eliminate by my estimation about 23 of our existing 48 parking spaces the church's site plan that was approved in 1996 has these 48 parking spaces on it per city zoning ordinance with 48 spaces we can have 192 people in our building that's based on four occupants per space practically speaking four people don't come in a car so in reality our occupancy is probably a lot lower than that probably one or two people in a car okay so our concerns of churches we need to maintain our current number of parking spaces which allows us to maintain our occupancy and continue to function as a church so if If this tentative plan moves forward, the question for the city is, how will the city ensure that the church maintains our current number of parking spaces? Thank you.
Thank you.
Yes, sir, I'll give you next.
Can I have your name again, sir?
John Lentz. Thank you. I live out in Sunnyside. I was born and raised out in Sunnyside. I worked at the junkyard for 25 years, only closed. So I know what is up there, and I know what's in Sunnyside. And I would love to see Sunnyside grow, but not the way they want them to grow. Like she said, affordable housing. Bring people in to build a nice little house. Why do you need a Taj Mahal to live in? We lived in a little shack back there where the junkyard was at. So we moved up to where my brother bought the house. He lives out there, lives there for 65 years. well what they want to do it does not fit in sunnyside yes we were the scum the city we were always run down didn't have stuff there but you know what there was almost there are 200 homes out there and we knew everybody now where can you go in this city and have that because we were a small knit community and now you want to bring in something this big it's not going to fit i would love to see yes small affordable housing and not what they're playing on what they do and i did live on the corner of duke and davis street my son bought the house there where like she said yes you know i'd see traffic coming down that street every day we sit down in new york traffic up and down up and down up and down and you want to put all this back in there on duke street there's going to be accidents all the time because people it's a 35 mile an hour feeling people do not do 35 miles an hour they go down over that hill and come up over that hill by the time you're on most of the garbage the bridge at duke street with the where duke or davis street is you pull out there them cars are right there for you and we see accidents there all the time so try that what he wants to put back
there does not fit into sunny side so thank you thank you sir yes right there sheila mcclucas mc capital c l-u-c-a-s as a resident of sunnyside i would like some clarification on this if he build 79 buildings and we're not able to build anymore are we as residents going to be informed because I have another property out there and eventually would like to do something with and if he puts 79 units in which you know is it gonna to limit what i can do on that other property okay the church has what three vacant lots is that going to limit what they can do on their lives um you know so that is a concern that i'm having at the moment um and knowledge you know nobody really seems to know for sure if he does 79 if we can't do anything else so that does need some clarification on our resident end maybe somebody wants to build on and they can't you know as families grow you know some of your families are parents grandparents and kids sometimes now because they can't afford to have a living arrangement all of their own okay so if they have to build on but they can't that presents a problem in the community that's my concern and being important is the number one thing with that
thank you mr albert if i could um we did uh i did find the copy of the search capacity verification request i'm happy to read it out loud i'm sure that would be appreciated it's dated september 2nd and was sent to jaclyn p holland at mac engineering which is the applicants engineer and it's a sewage capacity verification request the city has completed our review of your sanitary sewage capacity verification request dated august 10th 2025 for the proposed development project on the sunny side peninsula upon review the city finds we have sufficient sanitary sewer capacity for projected daily flow of twenty seven thousand five hundred gallons per day but not the requested twenty eight hundred thousand gallons per day the generated flows would be conveyed through the city's sunny side and stevens avenue sewage pumping stations with final sewage treatment taking place at the north treatment train of the city's wastewater treatment plant as of the date of this letter no sanitary sewer hydraulic overloads exist or projected within five years for these city facilities if the full 28 000 28 000 db is desired the sunny side sewage pump station would need capacity increased at the developer's expense all pennsylvania department of environmental protection sewage facility planning approval should be obtained as required no below grade basement gravity sewage facilities shall be connected to the city sewer system below grade basement gravity facilities are defined as fixtures with open sewer connections sinks toilets toilets drains washing machine connections etc located below the surface elevation of the city's upstream sewer line manhole cover for which the owner's private sewer lateral connects and then it concludes with his contact information that's
from brian harner from the city of lancaster okay so you're saying that the city said there was sewer capacity for 27 500 gallons but there was another number that was requested
28 000 gallons where it was requested so five um 500 gallons per day difference from what was
requested okay but that i don't does that answer the i don't think that answers the question of this like lucas about what that just says like this development can have 27.5 correct so there
would only be 500 gallons per day capacity left for for what for the um the north treatment train
of the wastewater treatment plant and that's the plant that services the sunnyside area correct
so but i'm sorry can you just um clear clarify how that would affect the other residents who are currently living in sunnyside and you know just let's use um i don't recall her name but the lady's example um she has another property on site if she would want to build something on that site would she be limited in what she could do because of what these gentlemen are
proposing to do right potentially she could be limited there's only 500 gallons per day left remaining on the site so how that's distributed is based on the number of bedrooms any other projects that are proposed i don't know the exact numbers of how many gallons per day you
need per bedroom thank you for bringing that to our attention okay who would like to be heard next
yes sir right i do i i excuse me uh clifford right um i was listening to the plans and i think joe's he's really taking a beating here on this because i remember when we were sitting in that same seat looking for approval for so we can catherine black can put her place in and we went through pure hell to do that and i feel for the guy i think this plan may need some adjustment there but also there's a lot of sore laterals in sunnyside that's not even being used because i think uh back in 1984 they well stewards went in like 85 i think something like that so i think like they took 200 houses out of there there was over 100 houses that were removed from sunnyside because the landlords didn't want to put the money into the houses to meet city code so there is a lot of laterals out there that are not being used now i know there's a lot of people that are not in favor with with joe's plan myself i could not afford that but we can't grow with you know in order to grow you have to have an open mind with things yeah he needs adjustment there's a lot of people even my friends are not happy with it i get that but at the same time what if it was your plan and you're trying to do this you know i just i just think it's unfair for joe to get beat up the way he did um and uh he's got some work to do i agree but i don't see it as a total wipe out i'm sorry sunny side could use some improvement maybe not 300 some thousand dollar houses but that's an expensive project do you buy the land that all the fees involved lawyers engineers permits plum you know it's a lot how do you get your money back you know those houses were a hundred thousand dollars or 150 000 a piece he'd never get the money back his children's grandchildren would reap the benefits from that project so you know he might have to adjust his prices I agree but in order to do something like that it takes money and that's why the city never developed in Sunnyside because it wasn't feasible for them because they didn't see no way how can you build low-income houses there's no money there there's no money to be made so I I think Joe needs a little bit of relief here I'm sorry community I i lived out there i know you people but i do uh believe in expanding i believe in growth and like i said i look at him as a what if that was me what if i wanted to do something you know wow yeah i mean but there has to be a change in sunny side you know maybe this is it maybe not but um i just want the panel and and my neighbors to give the guy a chance you know and and maybe help him instead of condoning the project give him some ideas some input hey joe you know what about this what about that how can that help help us how can we help you joe you know so so that's but bernie i'm just saying i remember bernie i remember when eddie had to go for permission to put the place in you're living in now it's the same thing bernie he didn't have
excuse me that's what this is well i'm just saying what this is about is by play back and forth with
the audience right right i'm sorry but i'm i'm just saying i we've all been here before anybody that wants to put something in out there we've all been here before for zoning to do that and we had to go through the same thing joe's going through his plans is bigger that's all but i'm saying you know when k when we had put signs up for zoning for her her place to go in i was worried to death man who's going to show up and oppose against it you know and what am i going to say to to to defend her in her defense you know and we did have lots of problems they didn't want her house out there it's too big it's too beautiful they didn't want it but we got it we it fought but thank god for mayor smith call charlie smith call he stood up for her and said it's going to happen but i'm just saying and now it's you know it's beautiful it sits right in there i'm just saying give the man a chance that's how i i'm a fair guy whether you like it or not i'm fair and i think everybody deserves a fair chance a fair shake and something like this or whether you're putting a single home in a trailer or anything and i i don't understand the sewer the sewage because there's a lot of units taken out so there's a lot of stuff that's not being used in the city for that and i think guy i think they need to re re-look at that i honestly do
because exactly i know that folks we're not we're not having conversations we're not having conversations among the audience we're here for testimony right uh you know i'm just saying i
just think the man deserves a fair chance that's all i'm saying okay thank you okay i would just
like to say that we will follow up with um the brian harner who is in charge of the the sewer capacity we'll of course follow up with him but i also wanted to just add that there some of this confusion over sewer capacity if you remember the plan was originally projected to be 65 to 70 units we also at the time were not confirmed on the what was being proposed on the north end of sunnyside with the environmental center and so all of these numbers have really only recently been calculated and so going back to that brian did also provide how he conducted the the estimate and so he specifically said that in terms of the sewer capacity request due to the tight constraints of utilizing the existing pump stations capacity he requested the detailed proposal and he asked that it contained the number of existing parcels this is all of sunnyside the number of existing parcels new parcels new housing units where sewer capacity is requested and said that's where and that's where it goes on to state that vacant lot parcels still count as new edu connections to the sewer system the city it goes on to talk about how many units are used so 350 for a three or four bedroom 300 gdp for gpd for a two bedroom and 250 gpd for a one bedroom and so that's again going back to using the bedrooms as the the capacity so um and that did include all of the unit that when you do the proposal that's how it's how it's done again i will reach back out to brian harner i've actually already emailed him to make sure that we can get clarification on this point because i do not want to misspeak but i i just do want to send that up as a warning flag i was
also advised that i should get sworn in i do um are we allowed to respond to residents comments okay so i i just want to respond to that comment of uh about like the open mind um you know i wouldn't be so upset if i was looking at a plan that had a diversity of housing types that was one of my big grievances with the sketch plan initially proposed to us and everything we're seeing is a monoculture so that that note about open mind does go both ways because we did offer comments to the developers as it relates to this project that we're not seeing put into this plan on top of that about process you know it this is a slightly different process than what a regular homeowner has to go through you have a single individual log you're doing a small project you're not quite going through a planned residential procedures, you don't have a public hearing like this, like this is all a legal judicial process. When it comes to this plan, I would be more amenable to development like this. If it were phased in smaller scales, you were said like, hey, I'm going to build 10 units, this is phase one, I'm going to build 10 units, maybe that's your storage units and some lots throughout the development and you're planning for future phases later on that incorporate other housing styles like this is just all at once and it's all the same so i i can understand some like yeah you've got to give people a fair shake you don't want to beat on them too much but this isn't the first time they've been here and from my perspective that there's not an open mind about the types of things we can see on the site
that's how i feel up here may i speak to that um mr dasher we uh we definitely remember the conversation from the last time and i um i do appreciate that um again reviewing the youtube video just refreshed me too like even at that meeting i think it like collectively uh your group as well as our group kind of landed at like this crossroads that it's just not possible to do a lot of different diversity the number one reason diversity doesn't actually work here is like we I mean we're already talking about the sewer capacity issue so diversity is gonna if we go up we're going to have to I mean that's going to increase the number of units and we don't have the capacity to put more units here so what what you have here is like flat residential homes which i appreciate they're on slabs and you call it a monoculture and i you know agree to disagree it is what it is but uh we have absolutely looked at diversifying the the type of housing i think all the past well not all but i don't i don't know about all the past projects have have looked at going up and and they're all facing the same the same issue it is sewer it's sewer capacity and so we have to do what we can with the cards that were dealt I wish we could do that the other the other comment that was made at the last meeting was we would have to provide sprinkler systems as soon as you go up and you're basically building multifamily that's an entirely different set of rules and processes we would need parking lots and dumpsters and all kinds of things um it's a whole different category in and of itself so i again then and also now we have waited it's not like we're avoiding or we're ignoring we're absolutely hearing you it's just not possible here this is like literally this is the best we can do that's the thing that blows
my mind because the eco district while we don't have ordinances drafted out in full it does specify lot coverage and so to the point of fulfilling the goals of the ecodistrict going up reduces your lot coverage which also goes in line with having more ecological diversity in the area i'm not a code expert but i do think four plexes might be able to have uh structures with
those sprinklers i could be wrong about that as soon as you hit three three it's so that's again two plexes a triplex you're instantly multi-family you are no longer residential building code but
But even the sizing of your units, you have units that are all the same size.
I mean, 1,200 to 1,800 square feet, two and three bedrooms is not the same size.
Do you have a listing of how many different sized units are offered? Because just from the plans here, and maybe there's more detail, but looking at these plans, they all look approximately the same size.
So we did that very strategically. So this is representing a footprint. That footprint, if you look very, very closely, it includes even portions of the garage and the private outdoor living spaces that are also required. Every home now is required to provide 75 square feet of private outdoor space. That footprint, we've strategically laid out the site to allow for any home to go anywhere. So if, again, and that is directly trying to get more diversity. If we said, oh, we can only put this specific two-bedroom right here, if no one buys it, that stinks. We did not want that. We wanted an ability for somebody to say, look, that's what I want. Or, hey, we want a bigger house. Can we get that house there? Yes.
1,200 to 18 isn't a huge diversity of range for me, especially when talking about multi-generational housing support. depends on how big the family is of course but three generations can get pretty wide and yeah I just don't feel the creativity has been explored here I don't know your pro forma looks like but as I understand it you acquired the sites for in total six hundred fifty thousand dollars roughly is that is that sir okay like you have a big site and a lot of room to play like like I said earlier if you were just talking about some units of housing i would be way more palatable to some of what's being proposed but you're just putting this across the entire site and that's what we can expect for the entire future of sunnyside then and that's that's concerning and disappointing
gentlemen can i can i jump in real quick everything that everyone is saying is valuable but can i just suggest that we keep the main thing the main thing like what we're here to to discuss, can we do that, because we're not gonna, everything isn't gonna get solved in our own eyes tonight, so can we just keep the main thing in front of us?
Yes, sir.
Arthur Morris, I do, Arthur Morris. I'm here listening to this discussion here and realizing that I look at these gentlemen and believe they're proposing something that's incredible. Doesn't mean to say everything's solved, but this is a heck of a site to try to develop with rock, form a junkyard. I came to this country in 1960. Three months later, I'm running out to Williamson Park, which is now the county park. We ran hills up there. We finished by drinking at the, there was a spring fountain about 400 meters from Duke Street. We lay down and drank water because we didn't carry a bottle since then. When I'm standing there, seeing people from sunny side pull their cars with bottles on them that they filled up to take back across duke street to their homes there was no running water there that was 1960. 1980 i find myself as mayor of the city i served as city engineer and public works director we wanted to do something about sunny side to help them so we put in water and sewer 30 years after they were promised it we put in water and sewer we improved the streets we had public meetings at the mennonite church we caught some help at some of those meetings because people didn't want the change but in general they agreed it was necessary and i know some of these people here because we held town meetings in sunnyside sunnyside was something i believed in when Brenna's quarry was threatening to grow close they wanted to fill the quarry up with water without doing anything we took them to court actually through the zoning here made them do some reclamation there's a bench part of that that's so far above where the water would fit so if somebody fell in in certain places it would be caught somebody needs to look at into that in the future as you develop the site but I'm here to say that i don't suggest that all these problems many of them shouldn't be looked at and resolved i do think there's a need to either say the city say we want to make this happen and we're going to work with you but you've got to meet certain requirements or you can throw all kinds of obstacles up i'm not saying you i'm saying in general and you can decide not to do it i wouldn't want to take this risk i think it's a heck of a risk that they've put in apparently 600 and some thousand dollars they've done two cottages i've been there i've told them i've looked at them i think they've done a heck of a job to try to make them fit in and no you can't listen talk about affordable housing they have no government money in this none nobody would do that you look at the developments downtown the market price is the right word most of them are market price most of them don't have affordable housing if you're hdc you get millions of dollars so they become affordable to ask these gentlemen to put affordable housing in yes maybe title it right i understand that but ask them to do affordable housing the money isn't there you can't do that so i appreciate your listening to the citizens and to the presentation and trying to work through this i hope there's a way to get there is what i sincerely say because i think again the quarry was operating it's not anymore the junkyard was there there was no water in the sewer we've come a long way and i simply say the sunny side have you say be involved but try to be a little open-minded
thank you thank you all right okay sir are you in the back i do george mummert i'm here tonight um
i'm a friend of joe's and a property owner on sunny side i have to say you know we've been through this before the site has its challenges its past and its present and probably will in the future as well i mean there's a lot to take into consideration here i have to commend these guys for their their efforts their fortitude and creativity the residents for speaking their mind for and against this whichever way they go and for all of you for the hard work that you have i have some questions um really for all of you um have we used this uh flexible residential development application type for anything of this scale before it's new to me as a planner I know we've had it on the books but I feel like there's an opportunity here both for creativity and for some forward thinking to address a place that we've had plans come before us in the past that haven't worked out to do something there excuse me to do something there is gonna take a lot of forward thinking and I think this board and others here in the city can work these gentlemen are here to work and listen to the public and to you and to make something happen and I think that's an important thing for sunny side seeing that we've had you know the history of what we've had there and the challenges of the site both physical and otherwise there's a lot to be done there i hear us talking about sewer i think it's important to address that obviously i mean i think through the gps that the city has you could probably figure out exactly what the build out would be based on the zoning and figure out exactly how many edu's and that equates to a number of gallons it's it's not insurmountable you can figure it out if the numbers need to be adjusted a little bit so be it but let's move forward with something here I hear the gentleman from the Mennonite Church talking about losing some parking spaces I used to be a planner for the county I don't know what plan he's referring to but it's my understanding that if you don't build those things within five years they have to go back under review again is that not the case i'm just asking that question and lastly i was just looking at an article from the last time we were here with 350 homes and in the article a former planner for the city of lancaster is on record saying that we could hold as many as 500 homes on Sunnyside I mean how would we possibly have had sewer for that and how did we get as far as we did with a 350 home capacity development did we have those same questions I would just like for you guys to continue what you're doing residents continue to be there listen to what's happening in your neighborhood and for all of you to continue the hard work you're doing i think you know we it's not easy to move forward and do something positive and i think our our rules and regulations that we have with our zoning uh you know tend to make what we all call sort of cookie cutter and i think this flexible residential development might allow us to do something that's different and maybe something better but we won't know unless we take the time to do it so keep going the very corner back there yes ma'am thanks george
susan shorty t-s-h-e-b-y i just have a few things i'm concerned with i'm 71 years old born and raised in sunnyside so our family is generational from my parents to me and now to nieces and nephews um i plan to leave my house in the family i have ground in front of it where i have room to put another residential building someone can live in with now when i'm gone i don't know what my family would plan to do if they want to put a house there for someone in the family or whatever My other concern is the traffic on Duke Street. That is a road, it's a racing road all the time. We used to call it the highway, because that's how bad that's traveled. And I think they need to do another study about how safe it is going in and out of Davis Street. Because I even drove out there, and it was hard to get out or get in in because of the traffic coming down and going up duke street and they people don't follow the speed limit so you had to really watch to get in or out and still stay safe another issue i have i want to know about um this is kind of off the wall since they're playing on 350 000 homes which are not affordable my home was built in 1925 out there it was remodeled in 1989 that was the year i first got water they could not jackhammer my ground they had to use dynamite because of all the rocks now if they start blasting up in the junkyard area is that going to affect the foundation of my house i'm like right against their property they need my property and uh it's sort of like in the hill my house and then the hill goes up i'm also concerned about drainage storm drainage coming down the hill what would that would do to my house also about the trees and stuff because four years ago we had a lot of wind trees came down off of that property and pulled the electric line out of my house and the fire company had to come out here and put off the streets off in case there was a fire i have lived out there long enough to see fires out there and saw houses burn down to the ground and then to be concerned about all the trees and everything it is a safety issue whether you're going to be up there or not i don't like the thing about the water resources for that it's not safe enough i don't think for you know i would be concerned and worried because if it's dry in the summer and there's a wind going and one of them houses might have a fire sparks deal with the air and those trees they catch I could lose my house or anybody else around there that's going to be close to the buildings you're going to be building. And as far as the junkyard, that ground is not clean. I'm no chemist scientist or whatever, but I'm not stupid either. That oil from the old cars, when they were pushed down to make room for more cars, That oil wasn't drained before they went to the docks. Some of them cars probably were in accidents. And you know, the fluid just ran out of the car and into the ground. And after all them years, and when it rained and stuff, that stuff went deep. It's not just a small area or close to the top of the ground. It's a good idea to take the soil off, but how much soil are you going to have to take off to get it to where it's going to be safe? i wouldn't want to have a house up there with plenty of stuff no way it's going to contaminate whatever is up there and there are certain parts if you look out there that stuff will not grow and then there's other parts of sunnyside arkansas and sort of the wooden stuff it's it's great i have uh stuff that the inscapers use for ground coverage where it holds the soil and stuff together it grows naturally in my backyard i mean there's there's um the environmental stuff the trees the plants there are eagles that live back by the park i mean there are you know animals too out there that some are on the they have to watch you're not allowed to kill them or whatever and i know a couple years ago they someone was allowed to hunt out there and i got really upset because they would go up on the hill behind my house and at that time i had a dog that kept outside and inside and i was always afraid he was going to shoot an hour or whatever whatever he was using and it wouldn't hit with the deer it would hit my house or my dog and i didn't appreciate that either so there's a lot of things that we've really lived without a lot of things because of the attitude the city had with our area and it wasn't only them it was also lamb peter when lamb peter owned the sunny side peninsula so this goes way back it's not just something new you know my house is only assessed at 46 000 now what does that look like against 350 000 and how many people living in magister that want to own a house a first-time house can't afford 350 000 i mean
that's the unrealistic not too many okay ma'am i i think that the the issue of the fact that this
was going to make that understood that to me that is not affordable but ma'am we've heard from about
eight people who've made that point already and this there's other people there's other
cases waiting to be heard i waited so i and thank you and i thank you for letting me come up okay
okay thanks mr mr gray this meeting takes me back i'll tell you
seems like old times tony i moved here in the early 70s the first time i heard a sunny side I should be sworn in, I'm sorry. Yes, I do. Richard Gray. Moved here in the early 70s. The first time I heard of Sunnyside was in the 80s. It was actually controversial whether the city should put water and sewer in there. The next time I got involved with Sunnyside was the Youth Intervention Center. Many of us opposed that because we knew it would screw up future development in that whole peninsula. Unfortunately, the county went ahead and did that. The next one, I was mayor, community basis. I wanted to put affordable housing in there. It seemed like I met with them monthly, 20 years ago. Oh, this changed now. Oh, now it's stormwater. We have to do this. or we can reduce this number over and over and over and over and over until finally we can't do it. They just gave up. Subsidized housing, really affordable housing, an awful lot of it, which isn't available today. The only thing I'd say to you is don't be 20 years from now when people say It was an opportunity to develop Sunnyside, but the city got in its way. Try to work out, and there's a lot of problems here. I sat here and listened to it tonight. There's a lot of matters that have to be resolved. Don't cut it short. Go ahead, work and see what we can do. See what these guys can do along the lines of what you all think is necessary. But don't do another 20 years down there. What do we have now? A juvenile reformatory, which shouldn't even be in the city. And an environmental center, which would be a nice addition to the city, but it doesn't solve one of our critical problems. That's housing. No matter what level of housing. One final thing, as Art said, no public money is proposed to be used in developing this. As Mayor Arndt and I were, look, how much will it produce in tax revenue? Somebody has to pay for the services we get. And this, I heard $600,000, $700,000 in tax revenue a year. That's how many policemen, firemen, how many other personnel can be employed. So I'd urge you, don't mix it tonight. just work on it massage it see if some of these problems can be resolved see how important they
are if they can't then move on thank you thank you mr gray okay at this point we the commission has heard a lot of testimony about the traffic about the environment about possible contamination from the old junkyard use and as well as preserving the character of the area uh in late of the hour does anyone have something to offer that has not been testified to before yes sir okay you've already sworn in so we'll hear from you again thank you this is dwayne brenneman again i just
want to clarify one point um one of the earlier gentlemen who commented seemed to seemed to be implying that um our 1996 plans were never followed through on i just wanted to clarify that the 48 parking spaces and the 23 that i believe this plan would cause us to lose was built and has been used for at least 29 years okay thank you sir okay is there anyone else who
has anything new to add that hasn't been covered already okay i'll take it your word sir dean
souter i'm the pastor at sunnyside mennonite joe mark thank you for your work the vision for the um for the junkyard i have been there for 25 years as a an attender i have never met a person there that was mean it's a wonderful community if you folks that i'm speaking if you have never been into Sunnyside it is one of the most unique places in Lancaster County and we would invite you I will personally give you a tour of the peninsula probably grab John to help me but no I would we would love to have you join us on a Sunday morning cell number visit us it will help you understand what they love about it and what joe and mark are proposing um it's just it's it's different and if you come on the first sunday of a month we do a really nice potluck okay thank you am i invited is there
anyone else who has anything new that was covered okay at this point i believe we're ready to close public comment it's the pleasure of the board to take an executive session or not does the board
see if we can move inside the case now i mean go ahead i just want to throw this out i mean i think mary gray does have a point and i personally am open to hearing more conversation about this site i don't know how it works but i know the npc allows for like mediation options and i'm just throwing that out there because i think there's a discussion to be had about the
site so there there is an option for that and so essentially what it would require it would enable joe to come back with an amended tentative plan but in order to do that he would just be required to waive the deadlines for the um right now we're going to the flexible residential development so we're on these very specific deadlines which is why the time we have the time constraints and so if if the applicant waves their the um the deadlines and gives the city more time then they would be able to come back with a tentative plan that addressed all they would have to address all of the um the notes that they have received that have already
been documented so i want to just make a point here that i think what you gentlemen are doing is commendable um i think that you have a big giant challenge in front of you you went from the little leagues with your two cabins to the big leagues now um and i also would say to the residents of sunnyside peninsula that change is always scary it definitely is it's not always welcomed but in nine times out of ten change is actually a good thing um so tonight i think that we're here a clarification for maybe me personally is to determine whether the current submission package requires the necessary details that the city needs in order to make an educated decision or if we can if it let's say it does not include that do we have the ability to work with the applicants to get to those goals it would be amazing to see something at sunnyside happen i question whether this is the correct plan i trust the team that is working on it i think that they have the best interests of the community in mind but i have major concerns regarding the missing details that the city still needs in order for everybody to make an entire or i would say a confident um decision to on how to proceed with
this particular application solicitor may i ask is now a good time for us to recess to discuss what
our options are uh i that that is certainly appropriate okay can you just restate the options that you stated earlier yes yes uh for for the record right uh the options got a little bit simpler because the applicant withdrew his request for immediate final plan approval the options are either for the city to grant preliminary plan approval or to or to continue the case or for their testimony or to make a determination to reject the application that's simple as the city's position would be that uh not enough information has been provided there's just too many holes in the application so well the other thing is uh you could continue the case for a hearing within the time frames that are here but that's that's another one those are the options to summarize we uh you know dismiss the application as being incomplete uh you continue the case to another for another date for another hearing within the uh time frame um or or you could grant preliminary plan approval and suppose that all of these things be worked out those are
your options tentative plan approval uh yes okay mr albert um i just want to say on behalf of the team here that a project team is open to extending the timeline to help address some of the comments that the city has raised so I miss Finn had mentioned earlier that if the developer voluntarily chooses to extend that timeline that that would allow us additional time in which we could address the comments and come back with a tentative plan that does that addresses of comments and is amended so just wanted to make the Commission and you aware of that well I appreciate the
clarification but the problem I have is that if the city commences its preliminary plan approval process then that that triggers the stays about enactment of any other ordinance and things get frozen and I I am opposed to the Commission the hands of the city being tied why a preliminary plan would be under approval for an indefinite period of time that's why we asked for a complete submission I have a question regarding the submission process in the
event tonight that we would reject their application would they have the same ability to then go through work continue the partnership with the city to go through the recommended changes and the comments that the city is suggesting pull the necessary details together and then come back or absolutely and that's
something i i want to emphasize is that if the application is dismissed as simply being incomplete the city the commission has not reached the merits of the case in any way we're just saying there's just holes in it we're not saying it's a good or a bad application we're not saying there aren't a lot of good ideas we're just saying it's incomplete there's not enough information for us
to act on there's no prejudice so could we have a motion on the floor no no no there's been no
motion at this point uh okay simply i've simply stated as the hearing officer that uh testimony is closed and it's ready for the commission to do something i i would like to move to go to
executive the board is going to take an executive session we'll try to keep it
as brief as possible but there have been a lot of points of view here here and I think you respect that there's some hiring out here to this board to come to
a vote looking at this plan on both sides the developers and also the community and we know that they deserve the best point of clarification mr.
Albert and mr. chairman does the rejection mean that a entirely new application needs to be filed or just that we come back to the Commission with
a revision of you know materials we need a new application it can be based upon the existing materials okay but it will need to be supplemented in terms of the
deficiencies the city identified okay so the application has submitted is dead as of now with the vote and a new application would need to be filed yes yes okay yes that is correct I'll just pass the mic here in case the two owners here would like to ask any questions about that gentlemen we'd just
like to encourage you to continue to work through this project there's a lot of gaps there's a lot of holes there's a lot of missing information that's necessary in order for this project to continue so i know that we just burst a bubble right now but you can fill the balloon back up later as you continue to work through this process so best of luck to you and thank you so much for your time your talents your creativity
we hope to see you back again thank you thank you with that the hearing is concluded i will turn this matter back over to the chairman for the remainder of your meeting thank you
mr allen number three approval of the meeting minutes for september the 3rd 2025 to have a
motion on the floor mr chair i will make a motion to approve the minutes from our previous meeting of september 3rd 2025. i'll second you have a motion on the floor
with the approval of the minutes September the 3rd 2025 ready for the question all in favor let it known by saying aye aye opposed ayes have it
motion carry
okay no i have that from the solicitor clarification from the solicitor and then i
added that um do you have your did i don't know if by any chance you had written down what you did um because i'll just need that wording for the minutes may i say it now yes mr chairman i will
make a motion to reject without prejudice the plan as we have before us this evening okay and then the clarification was help me out due to incomplete application do you have to say
which will require a new application or not no okay i appreciate that thank you it was just hard for me to hear everything okay moving forward mr chairman okay number four the subdivision and land development a 523 woodward avenue preliminary final land development conditional approval
i just also would like to interject here that this is a former rackel property the the property contract with Rackel just expired. And so the city is taking this property over again, and they're going to go through the process of condemnation and eminent domain for this property. However, your job as a planning commission is to evaluate the plan on its technical merits. So it is going forward regardless. And so it is your job as the planning commission to determine whether it is a viable plan and provide your decision as such. So your decision is the same, it's conditional approval, denial, that's not, I'm telling you this for your information regarding the owner, it does not need to impact your decision kyle will tell you more the mic okay yeah thank you
chairman polite members of uh the commission dr finn members of the public my name is kyle postalwait here from town square engineering representing the property owner which is woodward street llc represented tonight by mr eugenio humais behind me we're discussing 523 woodward Street. This property highlighted there with frontage on both Woodward Street and White Owl Alley, a public alley. The existing property has one single family semi-detached home or an end unit of a row home and the rest is totally empty, just grass and such. The existing home, as Dr. Finn mentioned, is being renovated as part of the Rackle process. But the proposed subdivision of this 0.142 acre property will create two new properties, thus bringing this lot to three lots. And the proposal is to add on two new units onto that existing end unit, thus creating a new single family attached unit and semi-detached unit both of the all three units both the existing and the two proposed would then have paved parking spaces one for each accessible from the alley a small sidewalk going up to the back of the house they will both be connected with new water and sewer laterals one for each property these are proposed to be fee simple lots I'll now discuss the other site features regarding stormwater management it is handled on each property separately so you will see highlighted here a small stormwater infiltration trench beneath the parking area and some grass area of the backyards of each unit and the last site feature I'll mention is the landscaping you'll see three street trees proposed on Woodward Street these will be the first street trees on Woodward Street and they are planted within a small planting strip that runs the length of the frontage so these will be the first three and on the theme of trees are one waiver requested which the shade tree Commission has already signified approval of is regarding street trees it's one ordinance section but sort of a two-parter and that is not to provide street trees on White Owl Alley and the second is for reduced tree spacing between two of the trees due to some utility conflicts these lots are on the slim side so to get 20 feet between each trees is pretty difficult here other past approvals I'll mention namely is a zoning variance that was granted in March of 2024 that allows a reduced front width and lot width that is and a lot area for the single-family semi-detached unit that would be proposed lot 3 here on the end instead of 25 feet width and 2500 square feet we proposed 24.83 feet width and a 2137 square feet I believe other approvals we already have. The city has adopted the Act 537 planning for sewage and the Department of Environmental Protection has already accepted that as well. And lastly I'll note that we've been through a few rounds of review with the city staff and their consultant already. And at this point the comment letter from C.S. Davidson is mostly clean barring a few little plan notation updates and little things like that and at this point any questions about the plan
i'd be happy to answer ms finn you had said eminent domain is happening at this property
no matter what so yes the um the property the owner has not complied with his rackle agreement and had gone through a process of um had he had received seven extensions and had still not fulfilled his requirements and so last evening at the rackel meeting they decided that they would not provide another extension thereby ending the contract for this property with rackel so i guess my only question is what good would even approving this plan do no that's a good question so um giving this plan a conditional approval would mean that while rockle is going to go through the process of having the property certified as blighted and then we'll take it by eminent domain they will go through a process of providing just compensation to the owner and then they will resell the property they will find another owner for the property if all of that should happen in one year the new owner would then have the option to fulfill the conditions of the plan and to record the plan and they would have a land development plan in their pocket and so that's i mean that's really the only reasoning
for it if i may um i mean it's a valid application that's been before us it meets all of the conditions of the ordinance and today is the date the last date to make a decision on it and because it meets all of those requirements of the ordinance we have to recommend that it be approved okay so
if i'm understanding right the eminent domain processes are going to happen one way or another but if this plan is approved whomever requires the property would have a land development plan
ready to go potentially yes does that does the timeline that you noted earlier um also include the city redevelopment um and the rehab i can't recall if this project had or was able to get to a rehab agreement through the city reinvestment board i don't believe there was um i there they
started with a rehab agreement through the property reinvestment board and that did not um go through i think it was a previous owner who had worked on that um and then that's when it was determined blighted again and then went back um through like went through the process of
condemnation and blight do you recall when the first initial letter of light was
the eligible um yeah it was discussed at the meeting last night i want to say it was um so at least the year was 2021 and when it started the process yeah i think it was 2022
when the whole thing ended yep so it's 2021 2022. i have a question um so this is dividing one
parcel into three that will be able to be done and the blighted property will just be one of those parcels is that correct and those other two would then be able to be sold am i am i tracking like
what well so if the subdivision goes along with the land development okay so they travel together
they can't subdivide and then now okay thank you and the city was um supportive of this plan yes
and again the square footage on a single unit is again um the square foot of the footprint
of the two proposed units are 969 square foot and 1061 square feet and they're two stories
okay thank you thank you any public comment motion on the floor can i make a motion to approve the
preliminary final land development uh plan for 523 woodward street yeah they would have to meet the
um the requirements that were stated in their last letter from cs davidson and you might just
want to make the like have a motion on the modification request before the street trees yeah unless you want to take the modification requests at the same time as the plan what do you suggest is best i would do two separate options two separate motions correct okay
start with the trees I'll make a motion to approve waiver request for street trees for 523 Woodward Street motion on the floor
wait for the question all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye motion
carry can I make a motion to approve the preliminary final land development plan for 523 Woodward Street with the notion that they will meet all the requirements
within the letter second and we have a motion on the floor for 523 Woodward Street ready for the question discussion all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye aye aye aye aye aye opposed hearing none motion carried congratulations thank you very much commissioners Jones Motorsports preliminary final land development conditional
approval good evening Cheryl Love with the LA group we'll review the plan briefly with This is the existing building for Jones Honda. It's located at 1335 Mannheim Pike. The building is rectangular in the back portion of what you see rendered here. The existing footprint is about 5,000 square feet. They would renovate the inside of that building, but there would be an addition on the front of the building, so the south side and the west side, and the addition would be about 7,020 square feet. There would be a 4,000-square-foot green roof on top of the new portion of the addition, so a large majority of the addition would be green roof in supporting stormwater requirements. Other areas on the roof are used for mechanical equipment and such. There are other stormwater areas that we are providing with this plan to the west of it there's some underground storm water storage there is an area at the back that is an existing grass area some of the green roof and some of the other components will discharge into a swale that exists back there we are improving some wetland not wetland excuse me but more meadow habitat with native plantings within a lot of the area at the rear area in that grass space as well as providing for trees new trees in that area that also provide some stormwater credits in the rear portion of the lot there and those trees are the lighter colored ones on the on the plan left side with regards to the remainder of the site it's it's minimal as far as our disturbance and what we're doing we are providing some additional landscape bed areas around the building itself some restriping of some parking areas some sidewalk improvements out front we do have shade tree Commission approval and their support and what I'll review with you shortly as a modification request that relates to street trees along the property frontage there are a number of signs of utilities as well as driveways that exist and within that space we've calculated what we would need for street trees so based on the frontage we would need a total of 16 new street trees we did work through discussions with the shade tree commission meeting to provide uh four trees lauren i don't know if the landscape plant it's can it pan up on that screen a little bit it's not as visual on oops i'm sorry uh i'm sorry if you if it keeps maybe you have to go down which direction there keep going down that the trees there we do have easements um out front that we are providing for four street trees out front um and then we're working the rest of the trees in we're adding trees primarily along the back portion where it's also helps for improvement within there's some general area along the back of the site that is floodplain area on this right end of the plan or the east end in that grass space so we're providing some tree plantings in there as well all while providing easements around all of those trees for ensuring that those remain in perpetuity and are required to do so so we have addressed most we're down to mostly administrative style comments um and we will continue to work through those otherwise um we it's a pretty straightforward plan i believe we have met the stormwater needs and requirements other than we have to share and provide an easement on the green roof portion on the top of the building which is not unusual for projects when they are providing green roofs to make sure those are maintained in perpetuity as well the normal stormwater om agreements developer agreements i think we have to settle on a number for financial security yet which we will work through those pieces you know with staff so um we've again it's decently straightforward from a planned standpoint but we're certainly and i'm able to answer any questions you may have i don't think i mentioned the addition is two-story i don't think i mentioned in the front portion so essentially it puts a new front face on the existing building that
is there currently as well the only question i have i appreciate the easement uh why the location and part of why i asked is because it looks like it was a curved room kind of like looking for uh you know this is gonna be a display corner almost I'm just saying this for the sake of the developer like I wouldn't want the trees to reduce their sales prospects even though I'd want to live without cars anyway well that is
also some of the discussion we had with shade tree Commission as a business and a car business obviously it is important to them not just from a visibility standpoint but that's their sales display area of their vehicles and the shade tree Commission was very supportive of allowing us to fit the trees everywhere we could which they are over some pavement so we are getting still some some heat reduction effect in the rear portion but that area is more of a service area and not so much a sales display area out front they do do have a number of signs there are actually two buildings within this one overall property so that's why this existing building is is rendered lighter colored but our focus the project is really involving the existing building in the rear which is it's a very unappealing building right now but it will greatly improve the visual look of that as well from the front while still supporting everything we could for stormwater on the new structure the existing
structure can't support that okay i i think i see them on the plan but there are new sidewalks
there are up front wonderful is yep all across the frontage um in fact one of our prior um one of our prior uh landscape architects did something for jones honda some time ago just to the west here and in fact at that point they were waived for doing any street trees any a lot of those improvements so we had to do some convincing to the owner that this is different these are new ordinances these are requirements and we appreciate that the shade tree commission was supportive of allowing us to provide an easement at the rear which also enhances that floodplain area back there and and some of the plantings in there without impacting the owner's use of the front display space for his sales of his vehicles out front so they understand they understand what the requirements are i did not mention five trees didn't fit there as well that's all outlined within the cs davidson review letter which we would comply with with a conditional approval would you recommend it any comment from the commission
any public comment hearing none on the floor i'll make a motion to approve the modification modification request um for the street trees for jones motorsports second we have a motion
in a second floor for jones motorsport any further discussion all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye aye aye aye aye opposed ayes have hearing none ayes have it congratulations
i think we need the second part we need the plan conditionally approved did i miss that no
i'll also make a motion to approve the preliminary final final land development plan for final land development plan for jones motorsports with uh the conditions uh in the letter second motion on the floor in the second
all in favor let it known by saying aye aye aye aye aye aye aye aye thank you pose thank you for your time tonight thank you thanks for your patience other business self-storage and zoning map thank you for your patience good evening i'm claudia shank with mcneese wallace
and nurik i'm here this evening on behalf of 1031 dillerville road lp i'm joined this evening by jim boyer with david miller associates who is the land planner for this project eric scott who is on behalf of the developer which is an affiliate of oak tree development and nate jones with storage construction who would be designing and building the proposed building for this property and alyssa quill with storage asset management who would be providing on-site management services for this project i did pass out a copy of the exhibits they're also on the screen but to avoid you having to look over your shoulder you have a hard copy there in front of you exhibit one in the packet is the property that brings us here this evening uh it's an aerial map of the site and what we're talking about is a two roughly two and a half acre unit planned community unit within a two unit planned community known as the dillerville road site association so the second unit there is the building that you see immediately to the south of the property that's highlighted in blue the property is primarily located in the city's c3 regional commercial zoning district there is a small portion of the property that is in the central manufacturing zoning district if you turn to exhibit 2 in your packet you'll see an excerpt of the zoning map the orientation is slightly different from exhibit 1 but you can see there again highlighted in blue is the property we're discussing and the pink being the c3 and the light gray which encompasses a very small portion of the property and the land to the north would be the manufacturing zoning district or the cm district the property is currently improved with a commercial building which is leased to an automotive repair shop and several outbuildings it's located along dillerville road we have been working on a proposed redevelopment of this site for a number of years and have been in consultation with city staff about that there are some site constraints that make this a challenging property to redevelop most notably and you can see this most clearly on exhibit one the property does not have any direct direct street access so it actually gains access to dillerville road via an easement over the adjoining shopping center to the south of the property so as a result of that we've been sensitive to the need to find a use for this property that would have relatively low trip generation and that is how we landed on a self-storage facility as the proposed use self-storage facilities are not permitted in the c3 district they are permitted in the adjoining cm district and so we are asking as part of our request to extend the cm zoning district to encompass this property in addition the facility that we're proposing to build is a little bit different than what i'll call a traditional drive up self-storage facility it's more in keeping with current trends to build taller facilities with more interior access to units and the zoning ordinance the city zoning ordinance doesn't really contemplate that kind of facility so currently the ordinance would limit all facilities to 20 000 square feet or less and the facility we're proposing to develop would be three stories and about 120 000 square feet so we're proposing to in addition to the rezoning to modify the regulations in the cm district to allow for a facility of this type in certain circumstances within the cm district and we did work extensively with staff on developing the criteria that would need to be met in order for this type of facility to be developed in the cm district specifically so i'll just run through those quickly now so first of all the property on which the facility is constructed would need to be between three and seven acres you may have heard me mention that this condo unit or planned community unit is only two and a half acres but the overall property um that the the tax parcel that the property uh includes is is within those measurements between three and seven acres and would qualify under the proposed amendment the building has to be climate controlled most of the building has to be three two or more stories except for drive-up units located along the first floor of the building all the units would need to be accessed from the interior of the building and there is careful thinking in terms of exterior garage doors along the front edge they have to be separated in some fashion from the street in the firm of a berm a screen some other buffering any outdoor storage of boats or vehicles has to be in the side or rear yard must be on a paved surface the building needs to be enclosed with the security fence there can be parking outside the fence but access to the building needs to be restricted in that fashion we have explored throughout the lifetime of this project which again has been several years the possibility of allocating a portion of the building for some kind of a community space we're not exactly sure what that looks like at this point in time I will share with you that the building that is on the second plan community unit or immediately to the south of this site was recently sold to heck construction so we have had some conversation with them about you know could they use some space within the building for some kind of an apprenticeship program or a training program again nothing has been finalized but we did build into this amendment some flexibility to allow for appropriate accessory uses within a self-storage building that may not be you know things that would be typically incidental to self-storage use so things like game courts public or private meeting rooms training rooms and other similar uses would be permitted as an accessory use in addition city staff has expressed a desire as part of this process to incorporate design standards that would apply to all buildings in the cm district not just self-storage that are greater than 50 000 square feet so we wrote those design standards as prepared by city staff into this ordinance they focus primarily on architectural requirements for building entrances facades and roofs and really they're designed to ensure that buildings are are visually interesting have some differentiation of materials facade treatments and the like sharing with you now if you turn to exhibit 3 in your packet you'll see three photographs of storage facilities that were constructed by storage construction these are just meant to be examples of what has been done in other places we do not have a design for this building at this point in time but this shows the variation that can be achieved and certainly the flexibility in terms of complying with design requirements like the ones that will now be in your ordinance if the amendment is approved the first photograph is a site in mcungee in lehigh county if you want to go to the second or scroll down to the second one that's a york facility with the move-in self storage and then finally the third one is in montgomery county in colmar again just giving you a feel for the different types of facade treatments that can be accomplished to create some visual interest at this point i would like to turn the presentation over to jim boyer and let him walk you a little bit through the site plan of course we recognize that what we're asking for here in the in terms of the text amendment doesn't just apply to our property but we still want to cover for you what what we're planning to do with our site if the text amendment is approved
okay yes we had prepared a site concept plan uh indicating how the property could be developed under the under the proposed uh free zoning and text amendment um as as claudia mentioned the uh the parcel we're looking at was unit b of the plan plant community which on the sketch is shown in basically a pink background so um you know as she mentioned there'd be the removal of the existing automobile service building and one of the other outbuildings and then the proposed self-storage facility would be in the center of the site work on this concept we're showing it as 200 by 200 feet in addition to the building construction there would be some reconfiguration of the parking and storage areas and also the addition of two gates to secure the the outside storage and those gates are between the building and dollarville road and then between the building and the rear of the property they're labeled there i'm not sure if you can see
them or not it's exhibit four in your packet might be a little bit easier to see them and those gates
are like i said to provide security for the outside storage which would be permitted in the side and rear rear yard areas in addition you can see in the on the concept plan the yellow hatched area is the access easement that claudia mentioned and that is a recorded access agreement for both of these uh planned community particles and as far as utilities the site is currently served by existing public water and public sewer and the existing laterals run from the rear of the property out to harrisburg avenue through a recorded utility easement and finally parking we did show some projected parking there maybe some adjustments as we work through the design but we would provide enough parking to meet the requirements of the city ordinance and also stormwater management at this point we're only the conceptual stage so we don't have any stormwater management designed or figured out but that would uh would be a part of the project although that being said most of the site is gravel and impervious now
already so any questions on the concept plan just to briefly cover some of the planning justifications that we believe exists for the request so again the property already adjoins land that's in the CM zoning district it's really an extension of that adjoining district the city's comprehensive plan does identify this property as being suitable for general commercial or industrial use which is what's being proposed here the design standards again which which were initiated by the city are also compliant and in keeping with the comprehensive plan that encourages ensuring compatibility of building design with the local context the surrounding area and then finally both the city's plan and and the county plan emphasize the importance of converting underutilized properties to to more viable use and we believe after much thought that that this is an appropriate and viable use for this site so we're happy to answer any questions you have i do just want to point out again alyssa and nate that are with us that have the expertise in operating these facilities and constructing these facilities so if there are specific questions going to those items i'll i'll defer those to them and i should say our request from you this evening is a recommendation to city council that they approve the amendment
to the map and text um i think that you're making sense to me uh i do have concerns about allowing more buy right self-storage facilities though in the community um and this is just a personal view i view self-storage facilities as a cancer on long-term property values um but i can recognize the constraints you're experiencing with this site um have you considered instead of rezoning and permitting more buy right self-storage maybe special exception use for the zone you're currently in so that at least like there's more conversation because i think this makes sense
yeah this we basically arrived at this resolution after I want to say over a year of conversations with city staff in terms of yeah Eric saying years of what we wanted versus what the city wanted I think we actually started out with something that was more narrowly tailored to this site and staff had recommended that we open it up a little bit so I appreciate your comment understand where you're coming from I think this is it's been a collaborative effort and that's how we ended up where we are
Commissioner? Any public comment? Lauren, I'm just wondering if you can give the city's perspective on this and I think particularly in response to the comment about it sounds like the city wants more, is in favor of more of this type of use in the commercial zoning districts.
i will i will defer to betsy but first i will also say that i would not i would not characterize characterize it as the city is in favor of more use of property for self-storage i think that we were working to find the best use um for this yet for this space in this district but i will betsy worked much more on the text amendment than i did so i will defer to her
thanks lauren um yeah so we did a pretty in-depth analysis of looking at a variety of different options for how big of a parcel it would be would be considered a good idea for that indoor self-storage especially is the current trend right now we anticipate that we would get more applications for it um currently our ordinance allows this type of use at 20 000 square feet or less in the r3 and r4 and as part of this ordinance we're getting that removed that's that's how the self-storage ended up in this sycamore ridge plan because they just went through the special exception process um i understand your your comments about going through the special exception process i think generally my analysis since i've started here is that we have a lot of things that require a special exception that maybe don't necessarily need to have a special exception which just increases the volume that zoning hearing board gets so i think if we have the correct standards that are in place then if they wanted to do something different they could go through that process and part of those correct centers is a
minimum acreage according to what i'm reading correct this what we're looking at is a minimum acreage correct yeah that's correct so it's not like somebody's going to come and do it right
there yeah and i'm happy to provide like the breakdown that we did um we really looked at like if it was three to five acres how many parcels would that impact in the cm district currently if it was three to seven if it was two to five and two like two acres with no max so we came to the conclusion that the least impactful would be the three to seven acres but also allowing the cm district to be developed do you have a map of the city with the cm districts like
how much area is cm yeah i don't i don't know if lauren can put one up but you're talking about the periphery of the city so i think another idea here is to to try to get the self-storage out of the core of the city in the residential districts where you may have people leasing garages and that kind of thing and ideally the larger facilities around the periphery would take
some of that pressure off i guess i'm just interested to know if we make this recommendation this evening how what um effects this will have for other particular parcels because like miss shirk i'm just i'm not familiar with the cm map district yeah i think if lauren lauren's getting
close to pulling it up so i think that might be helpful in just seeing which ones are um cm it's obviously not going to provide you with guidance on lot sizes for these you know the large massive projects so as um claudia referenced the majority of these it's the lighter gray are on the periphery they're in the annexed areas of the city um there are some along cm is along manor street which um with where kunzler was at as well as a couple little sections if you can see off of cabbage hill and then to the north um east walnut and um like that portion i did have to calculate the amount to apply to the county but i don't like the total acreage but i don't have that off the top i think one of our biggest concerns with the self-storage is that it was being allowed in the r3 and the r4 um i think as you you know obviously the city is older and there's a lot of kind of dilapidated self-storage like rows that um probably aren't the greatest use of that area of the property and just to note like the r4 and the r3 are like the darker yellow so in comparison to like just industrial i think it's fairly significant where they would be allowed as a
special exception so for given the the acreage requirements like i'm looking at like angleside
or like couldn't like the former kunzler property are those so the kundzler site is i think 2.8 acres um we just looked at that that wasn't on the plate when we've been working on this for quite a while i think i met with them the first week i started to be honest um so that wasn't
really like on the radar at that point yeah i mean i agree with not wanting storage facilities in r3 and r4 i just don't i don't know that i'm supportive of making it easier to build these kinds of facilities i mean it it seems like it makes sense for this site but you know they don't they don't create many jobs they don't you know they don't foster like pedestrian activity like and even in i mean even in this site like you you are right next to like a strip mall that
you know that has uh and some pedestrian activity so i don't know i i i'm i would be concerned about
like allowing making it easier to do this kind of thing and even in the cm districts i think that
they should be permissible but i think that they should kind of be like last resorts and i i can understand your point about the zoning hearing board having a huge load um but hopefully we can reduce some of that load with the overall comprehensive plan updates that we need to make i would take great reservation with approving self-storage by right in these zones but i do agree with eliminating it in the r3 and r4 any further comment i think the commission should consider a motion to maybe table this so that more like individual retrospection can be done about it but i can't make that motion so that's why i'm saying that how's the city what's the city's
stance um we went through several iterations of this draft ordinance to get it to the point where it's at and so at this time the city's in support of it so i guess maybe considering
some of my fellow's uh commissioner's thoughts and i think my concern is just the fact that i don't want to open up a can of worms because i don't want to see self-storage in other areas of the city but i do agree that it may make sense in this particular position i think what i'm not clear on is how this decision today will affect future development opportunities and understand districts moving forward and how that will affect the
surrounding neighborhoods i don't have i don't have a list in front of me but there are other
properties where this could occur i want to say it's maybe in the range of 10 or 15 other
properties where it would be theoretically possible now many of those properties if not all of them are already developed but in theory you know somebody could redevelop them for this use
so that possibility does exist i i yeah what the analysis we did with that there's 25 parcels that would meet these size requirements um and that five of them are vacant land everything else is in existing units certified that are vacant land that's a great question i did this analysis several months ago and i'm not finding the map that i provided with it so i'd also be interested
to know how this aligns with the uh com plan from our future plan first perspective in addition to the comments claudia already provided regarding it yeah i just from like uh what i what is that area zoned in the comp plan did you say that and i'm sorry yeah yes it's it's the the our parcel
in the comp plan is general commercial industrial is is the the goal for the future use but again it's it's being limited to to just the areas that are designated for these types of uses
not residential areas not commercial areas frankly we also look to see if it would have any issues with the surrounding parcels that are located in manhunt township they are zoned similarly they're a mix of industrial and commercial uses um so it would be another like transition phase it would just be extending it out it's not like a random spot that isn't tied to existing industrial
so if we yep through these couple years of analysis when you get it down to to five vacant properties, it's gonna be very similar situations to ours where if self-storage development is not permitted, you're gonna wind up with what we have, a dilapidated partial site with our lease is gonna end in February with Elliott's Garage. We have two Quonset huts. It's gonna be an eyesore. That is what this text amendment will unlock on a very, very small scale. really think it's smart land planning and use of the sites so i just want you know after a couple
years of analysis that's really what you're left with what is the current process if if this isn't approved is it just going to zoning and getting special exception or something um if they were to
to build the size storage facility that they want to build at that site they would need to go through the variance process so it wouldn't just be special exception because our ordinance doesn't discussed self-storage beyond the 20 000 square feet so they would need a variance to exceed that
by 150 percent we're not going to go through this right is there that much demand for self-storage i think now is probably the right time for alyssa to speak to that the answer the short answer is
yes i mean it's coming it's popping up everywhere it's an eyesore it's not nice in communities but it's necessary in some places this particular parcel i'm not against it i just i'm concerned about the sweeping rule for all parcels in lancaster can you come up please thank you
and i can plot the exact numbers right now in lancaster we manage 600 storage facilities but i live right here in lancaster and in the supply of self-storage in the state of pennsylvania is about eight square feet per capita in lancaster within and people use storage within a three mile radius of where they live so it's got a lot of people downtown and really only a handful of very small self-storage properties nearby the occupancy is very high and the rates are really high because they're full so the i think the supply i'll find the number but it's 4.1 square feet per capita the estimated demand is nine square feet per capita so people downtown are driving much further away to find the space and they're paying a lot more than they need to so this is a very relative to many markets i look at across the country this is very underserved what's
happening that we pent up demand is pushing all the self-storage into places it doesn't want to be can't really be controlled from a security standpoint from just the surrounding land value standpoint so this type of thing really does is push the supply where it should be in a very secure regulated safe fashion so it's it's a response to the pent-up demand market and also smart planning changing really the zone where it wants to be i think it's a smart idea especially
in the location i mean your traffic constraints are valid f m's right there though so the students probably could utilize that property a lot for self-storage but i think i don't think anyone up here is concerned about this specific proposal it's just a concern about what other proposals might come from it uh in the interim of like like i said earlier like we need to do the overall comprehensive plan update which isn't your fault um so i'd like to see you move forward but i i'd also think there is a need for pause that's just my opinion
right if we if we were to go down to like three to five acres um for example then that would be 16 parcels three of which are vacant land so that would reduce the number of parcels that would be impacted um which i think is honestly what they provided originally and we after doing analysis we're looking at places like where it would be an appropriate use jameel and i went through every parcel that was zoned and in that size range to determine if it would be acceptable
and that's how we came to that number i apologize can you remind me what is the acreage of this parcel because i agreed i love the idea there but if kunzler somebody buys it and buys just a little piece extra and suddenly they have 3.2 acres do we have a storage unit on manor street sort of thing so that's again my concern too and i was going to say could we go up to five to seven acres but you're saying this parcel is not going to meet that
yeah and i would note that the zoning hearing board recently approved a storage self-storage facility down by price elementary that's double the size of what's allowed and it's on a two acre site the city did disagree with that decision decision but the zoning hearing board made that
decision regardless i i believe we have not to belabor it or diminish the commentary we have here
but i do believe we have enough information to bring a motion before the board i agree may i make that motion yes i make a motion to bring before the city council to recommend the self-storage text amendment and zoning map amendment as delineated by example for
1031 deliver road i would just know procedurally if there's no second then the motion would die
okay there is a motion on the floor but there is no second so the motion
sorry so that's your Lauren so our options basically are to approve or
reject I mean you can recommend changes that you would like to see to it
I'm not just do the exact number of acres
We do understand the position to mitigate it, whatever the concerns may be.
Could we table this motion and collect more information from the city to understand how this could really affect other parcels? I know that you said that there's a number of other parcels that could potentially do this. I would be interested to know where those parcels are located and what the opportunities are on them for that, um and then revisit this conversation i think that's my preferred method to proceed without having the process start all over again i will just say that pushes us
i'm curious if we can use the transportation the transportation constraints as like it's by right but if there's a for example no frontage accessible by the road i'm curious
there was a version i had because i i'd be why did this process take so long to begin with not
to belabor this meeting any longer than it already is but it just seems like that's a long time to work on the text amendment so i'm just curious to know why it would have taken that long so far why couldn't this decision have been made sooner so then mr scott wouldn't be in this position where they're whether this this decision tonight would be detrimental to the decision
I can start that answer. It started with Douglas and we started well in advance so the city could address other planning issues in the eventual so we'd be happily obliged. We're happy to partner with the city and collaborate on the text amendment things up knowing that you're never going to clean everything up.
Yeah, I mean, I think that was part of like the transition between Douglas and myself.
We didn't mind that it took too long, but we thought we got to the end of the road where it's not a perfect solution. It's a very, very... Could you give us a month? I don't know what more information like that. I do respect your position. We've been working on it for two years. We have all the analysis done down to the number of parcels, even three to five acres, it's only affecting three vacant parcels, and if you do the language where it's not direct access, I mean, you've already said you have multiple, about sub-story development, so I'm not trying to purposely bring it to a head, but there's nothing left to be done.
Can you repeat your compromise? Sure. Repeat that again, go ahead.
i think we initially proposed three to five acres right and the city suggested three to seven so we're happy to go back to three to five and we're happy to i think at one time we had a language about parcels without direct access okay be happy to reintroduce that language because there were different elements everything you're bringing up was discussed at one point we'd be happy to bring right those two items in three to five that's more of a win-win i mean right we don't want
competitors and yeah so if we would make a recommendation to proceed with this um under the notion that we consider the addition additional terms of adding the street frontage language to it how does that affect the other parcels that could that are located with like
closer within the city we we didn't do an analysis on frontage when we were looking at the parcels so
we you mean street access not frontage but i mean i i also don't know that it's best practice to create a text amendment that's really catered toward i mean that's really what the what the
variance process is for so i guess i'm so the the storage facility that you said the zoning hearing
board just approved what was what variants were they requesting I would
say that's a little bit complicated it was a variance to exceed the 20,000 square feet by I think 100% was it 40 like 39,000 square feet so it was double the size I think there was some setback variances and then also variants to not
do the bicycle parking right against the trail one of the reasons i wanted to bring it to vote a is we need to right but the other thing is if this was residential we'd be ecstatic that they're using that kind of density for that property i mean this is 120 000 square feet and you're like oh my gosh who really needs that but again they're not wasting that space it's not a suburban sprawl it is something that kind of fits what the city should be requesting of any commercial slash whatever this is under things so that's plus by recommending it to city council yes it does have our stamp on it but they're gonna the public's gone you know they left two hours ago but they will have public at the city council meeting if they want to chime in and override anything we decided that's there um i don't expect a second it already happened but that was some of the reasoning behind it i think it's so clear on the plan what they want to do it's just a matter of
do we want to see that i agree with mr stolzfus this isn't best practice but i also think best prac best practice left us when we're two years past the comprehensive update um i i think this is a very reasonable compromise if we add the language about the street front restriction but that's just my opinion if i could make the motion i would do we have another motion on the
floor it's a three to five so if you were going to if somebody was going to make another motion you would need to make the motion um with the um conditions that you've just proposed just so that were cleared i'm not saying that you have to but i'm just clarifying and that was to reduce the size the lot size the lot size to three to five acres and um parcels without direct access to
public streets right okay i will make that motion for self-storage text amendment and zoning map amendment with the conditions uh to reduce the size of three to five acres for street frontage language and public access to the street am i missing anything i can second that yeah we
have a motion on the floor and a second and for the discussion i'm so sorry i'm just confused
why are we lessening the acreage don't we want to increase the acreage the lessening of the acreage
will make it apply to less lots less lots i was thinking so by going from instead of it being three to seven acres it being three to five it will include less lots yeah it would impact um
10 less develop like 10 less parcels two of which would be vacant so so the impact would be 16 parcels available three vacant but that doesn't include an analysis of the frontage and as claudia said she did that so it only probably one other person for the discussion all in favor let it
known by saying aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Opposed? Nay. Nay. Ayes have it. Motion carried. Congratulations.
We're getting to number six, staff report. Yeah, nope. Thank you, it's bedtime. Number seven, public comment. None. Motion to adjourn. And number eight.
We have a motion to adjourn. We have a second. All in favor by saying aye. Aye. Aye. Those ayes have it. Motion carried. Nicole, who did you second?
Meeting complete. No, who did the motion?